You are actively rewiring your brain for
the worst by engaging with social media,
high volume, quick videos.
>> And the social media executives don't
let their kids use this stuff because
they designed it to be addictive, and
they know that millions and millions of
kids have been cyberbullied, sextorted,
many have committed suicide. So, I'm
getting angry.
>> And then from the medical perspective,
it's rewiring your body, increasing your
risk of heart disease, and PTSD.
>> We've moved too far into the virtual
world, and the results are catastrophic.
>> People are spending roughly about 6 and
1/2 hours a day on their phones.
>> What do we do about this?
>> Well, here's the amazing thing. We
actually can control our fate.
>> So, we are joined by a social
psychologist in a Harvard physician to
dive into the technology addiction and
brain rot crisis billions are facing
worldwide.
>> And how we can counter its devastating
mental health effects.
>> You have to reclaim your attention
because without the ability to pay
attention for several minutes at a time,
we're seeing the destruction of human
potential, the human relationships, the
connection.
>> But there's all these small tweaks that
you can do to override that primal urge
to scroll. For example, 91% of people
had an improvement in attention,
well-being, and mental health after
[music] just 2 weeks of continuing to
use their device but not having internet
access. Next, keep your phone out of
your arms' reach because the sheer
potential for distraction has actually
been shown to change your prefrontal
cortex, which is called brain drain.
>> So, yes, we should exert more
self-control, but we're being pushed at
addictive apps, and it's messing us all
up. That's not our fault.
>> Would you advise people to delete these
short-form videos?
>> yes.
>> That would be the most important thing
you can do for your intelligence and for
humanity. But if I was going to offer
some specific advice, here are the three
things that I do with my students
[music] to reclaim your attention.
>> And then to add to that, I have the
3-second brain reset. So, first,
>> I wanted to ask you guys what you
thought of this.
>> Hey, you're back.
>> This terrifies me.
>> We've got to stop this now.
>> Guys, I've got a quick favor to ask you.
We're approaching a significant
subscriber milestone on this show, and
roughly 69% of you that listen and love
this show haven't yet subscribed for
whatever reason. If there was ever a
time for you to do us a favor, if we've
ever done anything for you, given you
value in any way, it is simply hitting
that subscribe button. And it means so
much to myself, but also to my team, cuz
when we hit these milestones, we go away
as a team and celebrate. And it's the
thing, the simple, free, easy thing you
can do to help make this show a little
bit better every single week. So, that's
the favor I would ask you. And um if you
do hit the subscribe button, I won't let
you down, and we'll continue to find
small ways to make this whole production
better. Thank you so much for being part
of this journey. Means the world. And uh
yeah, let's do this.
>> [music]
>> Jonathan, it's easy.
Jonathan, I've heard you say that the
destruction of attention is the largest
threat to humanity that's happening
around the world. And I've also heard
you say that short-form videos are the
worst of the worst because they're
shattering attention spans. The reason
why I wanted to have this conversation
today is somewhat personal.
And in fact, all of the conversations I
have in the Diary of a CEO are somewhat
personal to some degree.
Um they're inspired by some
unanswered question I have in my head,
and also some observation I have in my
life. And the observation I've had is
that short-form videos in particular
are
making my life worse.
And actually, I've got to say, the
catalyst moment
really where I thought, you know, I need
to get you and exceptional people
together to have this conversation was
I thought this, I then looked at my
screen time and saw a huge change. I
felt so much worse because all these
social platforms have short-form video
now. And then I actually heard Elon
Musk, who, you know,
has uh a social media platform that does
short-form video say that he thinks it's
one of the worst inventions for
humanity.
>> [clears throat]
>> Jonathan, why did you say what you said
about short-form video and this uh
corruption of attention?
>> Yeah. Because I wrote a whole book
called The Anxious Generation, focusing
on teen mental health. That was the
mystery that popped up in the mid-2000s.
Why are
people born after 1995 so much more
anxious and depressed? And I've been
tracking down that mystery, and it
points a lot of it points to social
media, and especially Instagram, social
comparison, all the things we know about
social media. When the book came out in
2024, since then, what I realized is
that I vastly underestimated the damage,
because I focused on mental health,
which is a catastrophe, but the bigger
damage is the destruction of the human
ability to pay attention. Without the
ability to pay attention for several
minutes at a time, ideally 10 or 20
minutes at a time,
without that, you're not going to be
of much use as an employee. You're not
going to be of much use as a spouse.
You're not going to be successful in
life. And that's when I realized this is
way beyond mental health. This is
changing human cognition, changing human
attention, and possibly on a global
scale.
>> Ditty.
What perspective do you come at this
from, and what's been your perspective
through all the work you've done about
brains and stress and neuroscience and
all these kinds of things that has
shaped the way that you think about
social media, screen time, short-form
video?
>> My background is that I'm a physician at
Harvard, and my expertise is in stress,
burnout, and mental health. And so, that
is the lens that I view all of this
through.
We know that the most deleterious
relationship that you have is with your
device. You know, in every healthy
relationship we have boundaries. We have
boundaries with our kids, our parents,
our colleagues, our, you know, with our
friends. And yet we have no boundaries,
and often porous boundaries, when it
comes to the relationship you have with
your device. So, it's not so much about,
you know, becoming a digital monk and
renouncing technology, because
technology can serve us, right? It
inspires, educates, connects. Now more
than ever, it's so important to be an
informed citizen, but not at the expense
of your mental health. and so what
Jonathan was saying this you know
constant being engaged with your devices
with social media the scrolling from the
minute you wake up until you go to bed
there's a reason why you have your best
ideas in the shower and that's because
that's the only place in the whole day
where you are not with your device.
People take their device to the bathroom
they sleep with your device you eat with
your device people walk down the street
there's more near miss pedestrian
accidents because people are walking
while they're crossing the street and um
looking at their devices. And so there's
all of this brain biology at play behind
the scenes. So both of you have talked
about how it doesn't feel good to engage
and constantly be on your phone that
sense of infinite scroll but there is
you know it's feel like you're doing
nothing you're just doing this right?
What are you doing? But in fact it is
not passive it is active and it has a
profound effect on your biology on your
brain on your psychology and also social
factors that I hope we talk about today.
>> You know scrolling wasting a bit of time
doesn't seem so harmful.
What is the big if we play this for 10
20 30 years what is the big risk or
threat?
>> The biggest threat right now we don't
even have to wait 20 years is that it
through a process called neuroplasticity
which is just a big fancy word that
simply means that your brain is a muscle
is that by engaging with social media
that that sense of high volume low
quality quick videos you are actively
re-wiring your brain for the worse. So
you're increasing your chance of stress
worsening your mental health attention
cognition distractibility irritability
complex problem solving all of that
changes when you engage in engage in
that infinite scroll.
>> Yeah I'd like to add on here because one
of the main arguments I get is this is
what they said about television this is
what they said about comic books this is
just another moral panic but people need
to understand why touch screen devices
are so different from television And so
I think parents find this helpful if I
just lay this out briefly, good screen
time versus bad screen time.
So, humans are storytelling animals. We
have always, as long as we've had
language, we've raised our kids with
stories, epic poems, all kinds of
stories. Stories are good.
The human brain needs lots of patterns.
The child's brain needs lots of patterns
to develop.
So, the worst thing you can do is hand
your child a device because they're
crying for it cuz they've been they're
trained to get it and you're busy so you
have hand the device, they're quiet.
What's happening? They're sitting alone
not, you know, when I was a kid we
always watched with my sisters, with my
friends. You're arguing about it, you're
talking and so kids sitting alone
with a device in his hand, it's not long
stories, it's never long stories. It
always ends up at YouTube shorts or
TikTok or Instagram reels for older
kids. So they're doing they're doing
this, but here's the key thing that it
does that a television does not. A
television puts you in a state that
psychologists call transportation. You
get into a story
and you find yourself pulled in and
you're rooting for the characters and
this is this is how a brain gets tuned
up to social patterns, but it can't
happen in 10 seconds. It can't happen in
1 minute. It takes a long period of time
and there is no reinforcement. There is
no The television doesn't do anything to
you. You don't have any response.
Whereas a touchscreen device is a
Skinner box. So, B.F. Skinner was one of
the founders of behaviorism and he put
rats and pigeons in a box where he could
deliver a reinforcement, a little grain
of food, on a schedule and by giving
them quick reinforcements for behavior
he could train them to do amazing tricks
in just a few hours.
When you give your kid a touchscreen
device, it's stimulus, response, swipe,
get a reward or not, variable ratio, and
then and and you just keep doing that.
So you are, as Didi said, it is rewiring
your brain. It's not just wasting time.
It is literally training you to do
things where television didn't do that.
So, this is a whole new game.
>> And to add to that, you know, from the
medical perspective, you're shortening
this attention span. And what happens
over time is So, like Jonathan said,
right? You're not sleeping as well
because you are engaged with your
device. We know that 80% of people are
checking their phones within minutes of
waking up. We have something called
revenge bedtime procrastination. This
concept of, you know, at the end of the
day, you're fatigued, you've had a long
day, you've had no me time, and you want
to get to bed early. We all know, by the
way, with the data is that, you know,
we've been taught since we were little
kids, right? Like, bedtime, sleep is
important, it's good for your body, it's
good for your brain. And we might have
all the knowledge in the world, but in
terms of action, there's a wide gap
between knowledge and information and
action. And so, revenge bedtime
procrastination is kind of an offshoot.
So, what happens? So, you know, you have
that decreased attention, you have that
irritability, hyper-vigilance. And so,
at night, at the end of the day, it's
9:00 p.m., you finally, you know, if
you're a parent, your kids are asleep,
your kitchen is clean, maybe you finish
your entrepreneurial day, and you
finally sit down with Melanie on the
couch, and you're like, "Ah, some me
time." And you know you want to get to
bed early, and you know it's good for
you, but then suddenly you're scrolling,
and before you know it, it's 2:00 a.m.,
and you're saying, "My god, what
happened? Why am I still awake? What was
I doing all this time?" What happens is
that you essentially give yourself some
me time at night. And so, you
procrastinate bedtime. And so, what
happens is with this revenge bedtime
procrastination,
it affects your sleep. And then when you
don't have good sleep, good quality
sleep, so you have difficulty falling
asleep, staying asleep, sleep debt over
time, for kids, for adults, has all
sorts of ramifications. So, this is just
the tip of the iceberg, this short-form
video content. And the ripple effects go
far and wide. Not only is it rewiring
your brain, it's rewiring your body. It
is affecting your sleep, which increases
your risk of heart disease later in
life. And um you're consuming graphic
videos and graphic images, it can
increase your personal risk of PTSD
through vicarious trauma, even if you
weren't there. So, this is just a vast
network of things that can happen to you
simply because you're thinking, "Yeah,
it's harmless. What is it? It's just a
bunch of videos that I'm checking out.
It's a way for me to decompress."
>> What do I need to know about the nature
of the brain to understand exactly what
short-form video is is playing is
hijacking
is taking advantage of?
>> The thing to understand about
all of this is that we have to focus on
childhood. Why do we have childhood? Um
humans have this really interesting
childhood where we we grow rapidly at
first, and then we slow down for about 5
or 7 years. We don't grow very quickly.
And then we speed up at puberty. Whereas
other primates, they just grow and grow
till they reach reproductive age, then
they reproduce.
But we seem to have this long period of
sort of middle childhood for cultural
learning. It's a period in which the the
kid is now walking and talking and
turning away from the parents, and and
that's a time for this to come in, and
they pay attention, and they form
relations. All these things have to
happen slowly cuz the neurons are
gradually growing, they're finding each
other based on what the child is doing,
okay? So, we grow up in the real world,
and and that happens over time, and a
lot of that is very physical. Kids are
very physical. Mammals are very
physical, and there's a lot of touch.
So, that's a healthy human childhood.
But when you give an iPad or a or your
old iPhone,
and they can they begin doing the the
touching and swiping, that is going to
hijack their attention, that is going to
push out all other forms of action and
learning, and that is going to change
the way the parts of the brain that
learn to pay attention, what's called
executive function. It's going to change
the way the brain learns to pay
attention. It's going to change the
reward circuits. I think you had Anna
Lembke on recently, who's our our the
nation's expert on addiction. And the
way that she describes it, how, you
know, any one addiction is going to
change your reward pathways to make you
more vulnerable to other addictions. So,
we're setting our kids up not just for
this, but then when they get a little
older, it'll be video games, it'll be uh
porn, it'll be gambling. Now, everything
is gambling. So, we're setting them up
for a life in which their brain is
saying,
"Give me something Give me some quick
dopamine. Give me some quick dopamine. I
don't want I don't want to work for
anything. I don't want to have to apply
myself for an hour and then get a
reward." And so, the what the short
videos are doing for kids is preventing
them from learning the connection
between hard work and a reward.
>> Is there anything else I need to know
from a neuroscience perspective about
what's going on in my brain when I'm
when I develop these addictions with
short-form videos or these sort of quick
dopaminergic tasks?
>> So, we all as humans have a primal urge
to scroll. When you feel a sense of
stress, as many of us do in this moment
in life, it is your sense, you know,
your amygdala. And so, it's your sense
of self-preservation. It's survival and
self-preservation. That is what your
amygdala does. So, if you want me to
show you here,
>> what I'm doing though.
>> Yeah, it's okay. So, here,
deep here, it's a small almond-shaped
structure, and that is your amygdala.
And your amygdala, its main purpose is
survival and self-preservation. It
houses your stress response, your fight
or flight response, and it is truly what
is activated when you are engaging in
content, when you feel a sense of
stress, and so you have this primal urge
to scroll. And so, evolutionarily, we we
when we all were cave people living um
together, we would sleep at night, and
there would be a night watchman scanning
for danger. And now, we have our we we
have become our own night watchman, and
so we scan for danger all day, all night
long. How do we do that? We scroll. And
then the amygdala is triggered, and then
you scroll some more, and you scroll
some more, and you scroll some more. And
so, over time, what you're doing is that
you're making that amygdala in a state
of of chronic it's continually being
triggered.
What happens to the amygdala over time
when it's continually triggered? It
starts to rewire your brain in other
ways. And how does it do that? Through
something called
the prefrontal cortex. If you put your
hand I like I can use this model but I
can also just use my hands. When you put
your hand on your forehead the area
right behind your forehead right here is
the prefrontal cortex. This is a very
important thing for our conversation
this area of the brain. And what the
prefrontal cortex does is it is called
it governs executive functions. So
impulse control, memory, planning,
organization, strategic thinking,
complex problem solving. And there is a
tension between your amygdala and the
prefrontal cortex. When your amygdala is
in the driver's seat that prefrontal
cortex is quiet. And what is happening
as we continue to engage with our
devices and have this primal urge to
scroll that amygdala upregulates and the
prefrontal cortex down regulates. And
over time that is very problematic for
all of the reasons that we're kind of
introducing at the start of this
conversation.
>> There was a meta-analysis done in 2025
of 71 different studies and it found
that heavy short-form video use was
associated with reduced thinking ability
especially shorter attention spans and
weaker impulse control.
>> That's right.
These studies are just beginning to roll
in now. Um kids have been on social
media really a lot since 2008 but
especially once they got smart phones
around 2012. Studies began coming in uh
in the 2010s that um look it's looking
like the kids who are spending a lot of
time on this
um are doing much worse. They're more
depressed. The focus was on depression.
And some other researchers said no it's
just a correlation you you that you
can't prove causation. And we've been
going around and around on this for
about 10 or 15 years. Now we're doing
the same thing with uh with the
short-form videos.
The damage everyone can see.
My students tell me this is what's
happening. We feel it. Studies are
coming in, but there will be a few
studies here and there that don't show
it and people will
push that up. Meta were spends a lot of
time and money to influence the public
debate. A lot of public documents are
coming out now about how they do that.
So, we can engage in debate over over
research on short-form videos for 5 or
10 years, but at that point it's way too
late and we've lost a second generation,
Gen Alpha. So, I think when we're
talking about kids especially, we need
to have what's called the precautionary
principle, which is if there's reason to
think that this is hurting kids, how
about we don't roll it out into every
childhood? How about we make these
companies responsible? We hold them
responsible for what they're doing to
kids because we're about to make the
same mistake we made with social media,
letting it worm its way into childhood.
We have already done that with short
videos and we're about to do it with AI
chatbots. In fact, we're just beginning
it in late 2025, I'd say.
>> I don't think people quite realize how
much these major media platforms have
figured out that short-form video sells.
Um we're actually seeing this sort of
global rise in short-form drama apps
now.
I don't know if you guys have seen these
apps, but it basically takes a movie
that what used to be 2 hours long and it
breaks it down into say 60 different
parts. My colleague of mine at my
company was showing me the other day in
different parts of the world they're
exploding. There's been a 190% increase
in short-form drama apps. Takes a
long-form movie, turns into short-form
videos. Disney Plus plans to introduce
AI-generated short-form videos this year
starting with 30-second limits inside
the Disney Plus app and TechCrunch also
reported
that as of October 2025, Netflix tested
short-form video content on phones and
recently announced its plan to expand
this feature. It appears that all of the
content we consume is going that way.
And listen, I'm friends with lots of
people at big social media platforms.
This doesn't get me this doesn't stand
in my way of criticizing them cuz
I think two things can be true at the
same time, right? So, I I think it can
be true that I have a podcast and I make
short form videos and that I also
understand that there's a real
downside to them. And all of the major
social social media platforms that I
speak to speak to have a huge drive
towards short form video. It is It
appears to be their number one strategic
priority and
obviously because of the success of
TikTok. As of January 2026, TikTok, I
believe, is the most downloaded social
app in the world now.
And it
If I'm running a social media company
and my one focus is profit,
I'm now faced with an existential
crisis. I either take part in this thing
that is driving the highest retention,
therefore
the best ad payouts,
or I die.
>> So, there's two comments to that. First
off is that, you know, when we think
when we think about social media and how
society is shapeshifting to allow the
short form content, there is a concept
that Jonathan and I briefly mentioned I
think as filming called second screen
viewing. And so, what's happening is
that allegedly these big streamers are
asking their creative talent, whether
it's screenwriters or actors or
directors, to replay to reiterate the
plot because as you're watching, you
know, when we were kids, we would watch
TV or movies and you'd just sit on the
couch and you'd have a bucket of popcorn
with your family and you'd watch a movie
an hour, hour and a half, two hours. And
now second screen viewing is happening,
which means that you're watching a movie
or a TV show and you're on your device.
And so, you are constantly having that
fragmented attention and we are all
doing it. And so, what these streamers
are allegedly asking their creative
talent to do is to reiterate the plot.
So, it's shapeshifting.
>> If my brain is, you know, I'm 33 years
old, so I've grown up with a lot of this
stuff.
If my brain has been wired to have
shorter attention spans and and
movies from 30 years ago are not going
to cut it for me.
>> Right, but then look what happens if if
everybody chases that and I know look
Netflix is making shorter and shorter
stuff. Even Ted, the Ted conference, Ted
talks are getting shorter and shorter.
What does that do? It just repeats the
cycle. Now, I appreciate that you're in
a collective action trap as you put it.
If I don't do it and everyone else is
then I lose out and so the the business
pressure on on all the creators, the
business pressure is go shorter shorter
shorter.
There's a very useful psychological term
distinction here that I think will be
helpful, which is the difference between
psychological assimilation and
accommodation. This goes back to Jean
Piaget, the great developmental
psychologist. We we have certain mental
structures. We have a a model in our
head of how things work. And you know,
then you learn something new then oh,
that's a you know, kid learns oh, that's
a an aardvark. Okay, I put that into you
know, that's just it you just
assimilate. They learn lots of animal
names.
And then they learn something that's
doesn't fit. Like you learn about
bacteria. And now you have to okay, now
you have you have
you have to change your mental
structure. It takes a little time. You
change your mental structure to
understand more about life. That's what
education really is all about. You have
to have a lot of assimilation, of
course, but you need that accommodation
over and over again. That's why you want
to go to college. That's why you want to
read novels. That's what a great movie
does. It takes time.
And so one of the great things about
this modern technology is that we can do
things like have this 3-hour
conversation. I can't believe it. People
are going to listen to it. So, this you
know, long-form content, this is all
about accommodation. Anybody who walks
out who who who leaves this conversation
after 3 hours and isn't thinking about
something differently, we failed. Okay?
So, you are very much in the
accommodation business. That's great.
And then the the question, both a moral
and a strategic question, is
how much do you need to play the the
quick hit game in order to get people
there? I leave that to you to do the
moral calculation. Maybe it Maybe it
balances out. Maybe but but I think
that's where you are.
>> Would you advise people to delete
these short-form videos?
>> yes. Of course.
Here but here yes, that would be the
most important thing you can do for your
intelligence and for humanity would be
delete them. So, what I advise my
students to do is
I say just do this. Just just delete
one of the social media apps that you
use, especially if it's TikTok. Just
delete it from your phone.
You can still check on your computer. If
someone sends you a video, you can still
watch it on your computer. You can even
check it, you know, every weekend you
can spend some time on it. But just get
it off your phone because on the phone,
the phone is always with us. It's an
extension of our body. And if it's
always there, then it's going to take
every It's called attention fracking.
It's going to break up your attention.
It's going to take every 7 seconds that
you're not doing something, you're going
to go for the phone.
So, the best thing you can do to make
yourself smarter and a better partner
and a better human, I would say would be
to delete the short especially any of
the short-form videos. So, TikTok.
Unfortunately, YouTube which has a lot
of good stuff on it, becomes YouTube
shorts. Instagram which does a lot of
terrible things, but people do find it
useful for all kinds of purposes becomes
Instagram reels. So, I think the proper
amount of short-form video for children
0 to 18 is zero. They should never be
watching the vertical videos. Parents,
don't ever let your kids watch the short
vertical videos. You might even if they
were if only there was a way to put it
Is there a way to put a time limit where
you can say has to be 10 minutes or
longer. Kids, you can have an hour of
YouTube, but it has to be 10 minutes or
longer. Nothing shorter than 10 minutes.
That at least will get rid of this the
quick the quick swiping the the dopamine
stuff.
>> So, I would say that for kids, yes,
like, you know, not engaging at
whatsoever. But for someone, you know,
my approach is a little bit different
for someone who's like in their 30s or
in their 40s. And the way I would kind
of frame that is
instead of renouncing, you know, saying
I'm going to get it off my device and
I'm going to check on a desktop, which
is great. There's little kind of tweaks
that we could do because my approach is
to foster that sense of empowerment in
someone to help them make positive
change. And so one strategy that you
could use if you are saying there's no
way I'm getting rid of my I'm not
deleting these apps from my phone,
right? If you're By the way, I practice
what I preach and I really do don't
engage in technology as to the best of
my ability.
Um but one thing that you could do is
grayscale your phone. And so especially
at night, like it's 9:00 p.m. like we
talked about revenge bedtime
procrastination, you know that you're
going to do it. You're going to sit down
and you're going to scroll and before
you know it it's 2:00 a.m. Instead,
grayscale your phone. This is a simple
switch, you can toggle it. I have my
phone set to grayscale, which simply
means that you're getting rid of your
color, making it black and white. And so
when it is gray scaled, then you you
know, it doesn't have that same
addictive quality to it. It's like going
through a grocery store. A marketing
executive described it this way to me.
Going through a grocery store instead of
the Technicolor junk food cereal, it's
just black and white. So you have a less
there's a greater sense of compulsion to
continue checking. So that's like one
strategy you could use. And the other is
to set some boundaries. So geographical
boundaries, keep your phone out of out
of your arms' reach. If you're at a
desk, if you're a student, not right
next to you because we know there's this
phenomenon of brain drain. So it's not
just that when you're using your phone,
it can have a potential for distraction,
but also just having it close by. It's
called brain drain. And um so putting it
in a desk drawer, keeping it in another
part of the home. If you are working,
keeping it far away from you. And so you
kind of can override that primal urge to
scroll that your prefrontal cortex take
hold again. And so there's all these
small tweaks that you can do. You You
think no?
>> Yes, there are all these small tweaks
you can do and they will make the heroin
a little bit less addictive. And yeah,
you should try those. But what I can say
after teaching this course for many
years is that people who try that they
they put Yeah, you know it helped. It
helped. But you only really get the
transformation when you quit social
media. That you get your life back, you
get hours a day back. So,
um
and so I I would urge everyone to just
think, you know, you only
you only get one childhood, you only get
one one one young adulthood. And if
you're going to spend it scrolling, what
do you have to show for it at the end?
And when you get people to reflect on,
well, how much value do you really get
from watching the short videos? What
would How would your life be different
if you if you knocked it out? Once they
realize that their motives for being on
it were either just to keep up or
because that's what everyone else is
doing, or as you said, I deserve it
because I'm tired. Well, why are you
tired? It's in part because your
attention was fragmented all day long.
So, you only really get the
transformations when you get a real
change in what you're what you're
consuming. Although, of course, yes,
setting your grace would be helpful, but
it's not going to be transformative for
most people, I believe.
>> And then, you know, based on the
science, there are there are certain
elements like when we think about what
is it about the phone that is creating
that sense of compulsion? Jonathan is
right. So, what is it about the phone?
It's not just the phone, you know,
you're scrolling, you're engaging. There
are two studies that were really
interesting. One, people got off of they
they continued to use their devices,
they had no internet. So, it's like, you
know, I I I tried this experiment myself
in December. I was out of the country,
and so I just let my, you know, I didn't
plug into Wi-Fi. And I found, you know,
markedly marked change in my mood, my
sleep.
And I'm not even, you know, 20 years old
on TikTok. And it was so different. And
so the study found that just 2 weeks of
continuing to use your device, but just
not having internet access, improved
your attention, well-being, and mental
health. And in this population, it was
all adults, it wasn't kids. It was all
adults.
Found that 91% of people had an
improvement in at least one of these
metrics. And then another study, more
recently, just 1 week of not engaging in
social media,
a digital detox they called it, did the
same thing.
Better, you know, less anxiety, less
depression,
decreased insomnia.
But my feeling is that, you know, there
is this new kind of meme, right? Like
you're the millennial urge to delete uh
my internet presence and you know, live
off the grid. There is certainly utility
to that and I salute anyone who wants to
engage in that analog life more and
more. But
from my from where I sit, I feel like we
do need to have healthier boundaries and
engage more responsibly. It also builds
up that muscle and it can help, you
know, takes 8 weeks to do.
Neuroplasticity, when you're building
new brain circuits, it takes 8 weeks.
Falling off, getting back up is part of
habit formation. So if you're going to
make any of these changes, understand
that it takes some time. But I
I don't know if it is possible
for me or for others to say fully, I'm
going to, you know, delete off of my
phone. But I love that.
>> So I'd like to go go a little further um
a little further with this.
So the way you the way you put it, yes,
there's all these things that we could
do, we should have boundaries. But all
of that puts the responsibility on us.
>> Agreed.
>> where we are with junk food. With junk
food we're like, "Okay, it's out there.
We have to learn self-control. We have
to teach self-control to our kids."
Okay, that's the way it is in this
country. But the digital device I think
are very very different. So imagine if
Imagine if we sent our kids out into the
world and it wasn't just that there was
junk food in all the stores. It was that
everything was made of junk food. You
know, you you know, the door handles,
you can eat it, it's chocolate. But it's
not just that the world's made of junk
food, it's they actually can tell
uh they're able to tell what you're
craving at the moment and maybe you're
you're more in the mood for salt. So So
now it's all potato chips or pretzels.
If the world is designed by companies to
always give you the thing that will most
grab your unconscious desires. Will
affect the amygdala, the reward centers.
That's on them. That's not our fault.
My general rule as a social psychologist
is if a few people are doing something
bad or self-destructive, well, you know,
they should learn some self-control or
that's something about them. But when 90
or 95% of people are doing something
self-destructive,
that's because of the companies that put
us in an environment that encourages
addiction. So, I just want to read a
quote. We have so much good stuff coming
out from Meta, from all the
whistleblowers. Now, all the court cases
are beginning in Los Angeles. Finally,
for the first time, they're going to
Meta's going to face a jury with all the
parents who've lost kids. Um
so, here is Here's the the chat. So, we
have a lot of internal documents that
came out from the the attorneys general
that are suing Meta.
So, while they're talking about the
results of some of their internal
research, one of them says, "Uh oh my
gosh, you all, Instagram is a drug.
We're basically pushers. We're causing
reward deficit disorder because people
are binging on Instagram so much, they
can't feel reward anymore." Which is
something Anna Lembke said.
>> [snorts]
>> Like their reward tolerance is so high.
And then he says, "I know Adam," meaning
Adam Mosseri, "I know Adam doesn't want
to hear it. He freaked out when I talked
about dopamine in my teen fundamentals
leads review. But it is undeniable. It's
biological and psychological. Top-down
directives drive it all towards making
sure people keep coming back for more.
This is not on us. They designed it to
be addictive. They've done research to
make it maximally addictive. They push
it on children. They tried to get
Instagram kids for even littler kids.
They know what they're doing. They've
done the research. My team, we put
together, we found references to 31
internal studies that Meta did. They've
done a lot of research finding harm.
They bury it, but you can find it at
metasinternalresearch.org.
We put it all online. You can read these
quotes. So, yes, we should exert more
self-control, but basically we're being
pushed addictive substances, addictive
addictive apps, and it's messing us all
up.
>> I agree wholeheartedly that it is so
destructive, and you feel like even with
people in their 40s and 50s, and if
anyone can do it, it's you, Jonathan.
Seriously, I would love to see it. You
know, we also know, based on the data,
that these things quite they they
reshape our brain, rewire our brain
through neuroplasticity, and also change
our brain waves, so patterns. So, we
talked about the amygdala and the
prefrontal cortex, right? But they also
change brain waves. And so, when you
look at studies and the data, it has the
reward pathway and dopamine, and these
brain patterns, the brain waves, mimic
addictive behaviors. And, you know, that
there's certain features, right? Like,
when you do swipe down to refresh, it's
the slot machine.
>> It was modeled directly after the slot
machine, yeah.
>> Or autoplay, or you know, the algorithm,
that infinite scroll.
One really interesting kind of like
breaking news, which you guys may have
already heard of,
it's like 3 days ago, the European Union
Commission found TikTok to be in breach
of the Digital Services Act. And what it
said was that it is addictive, it
you know, creates compulsion, and gets
people into this autopilot mode, so they
have difficulty disengaging. And
personally, I am moving away from social
media and really leaning into analog
life. But I think with the way the
world, you know, it's one of our only
ways to connect, right? Meaning, I don't
mean connect deeply. I don't I don't
mean connect like in a deep way. But be
informed, to know what's going on in the
world, etc.
>> I I suspect that because we've spent so
long criticizing Meta over the last 10
years, because the biggest in any
category takes all the heat. So, OpenAI
is taking it now. And what this often
does is is it provides cover for other
people to go even more extreme with that
behavior while like meta take the heat.
And I actually think this is how TikTok
came to be. TikTok had basically the
originally started as musically became
TikTok. They had they would take they
were taking no heat.
Um so they they created an algorithm
which is the equivalent of like crack
cocaine. The reason why I have a TikTok
account, I don't have the app on my
phone. I have never had the app on my
phone.
I don't I don't
was because I I noticed that the view
variance on TikTok was like no other
platform. What I mean by that is you can
have a million followers on TikTok and
you can get 10,000 views or you can get
10 million views.
In the 15 years that I've been on social
media building social media businesses,
I'd never seen this before. And what it
indicated to me is that the algorithm
was being an even more aggressive
sorting hat or retention machine.
>> up, what to push down.
>> Yeah. And so like when I started in
social media in 2014,
if I had a million followers, I might
get a million views or maybe 800,000.
I did some research the other day on all
of our social channels over time. And
what we're seeing is the variance in the
amount of views we can get is
increasing, which means the algorithm is
doing more work to say show everyone
this. I don't care if the person that
posted it is called Jenny and has seven
followers and show no one this. I don't
care if it's Steven who has a million
followers or whatever. And I've realized
that TikTok was was way ahead of
everybody here. And that's why they are
the most addictive, the fastest growing
platform. I say all this to say that
even if meta shut down tomorrow,
someone else would seize the opportunity
if there isn't sort of policy, I would
suggest, in place.
>> That's right.
>> It'd be whack-a-mole, right?
>> Yeah. No, that's right. And so, you
know, in terms of who's done the damage
to kids, meta is the big fish via
Instagram. And they're also the main
player in terms of spending a huge
amount of money to lobby Congress and
change and block laws. They're also the
main player in buying up civil society
organizations, giving money to
organizations, the national PTA, all
sorts of organizations. They get to then
give a message on digital citizenship or
digital health.
So Meta really is the major driver. Meta
is the tobacco industry here trying to
change the the dialogue. But in terms of
the products, um Snapchat is probably
more deadly in terms of the actual
number of deaths per user cuz Snapchat
is not is not making you depressed by
social comparison as much. Snapchat is
introducing you to all kinds of people
and it's the main way that drug dealers
and and sextortionists find kids.
Snapchat has a quick add feature which
relentlessly pushes you to connect with
friends of friends. So once a man can
get any friend any kid in a school, now
he can get connected to all the kids in
the school. So uh when we in a lot of
the court cases, you know, when you have
you have suicides from cyberbullying,
you have drug overdoses from you know,
kid bought a Xanax but it had fentanyl
in it. So Snapchat [snorts]
at Snapchat in in 2022, we know from
their internal documents from the
lawsuits,
they were getting 10,000 reports of
sextortion from their users. Not a year,
every month. And that's just what was
reported which is the tip of the
iceberg. So Snapchat [snorts]
is a terrible platform for children to
be on. It should be an adult-only
platform. You're talking with strangers
around the world and and on with
disappearing messages and Snapchat
doesn't even keep a record. It is ideal
for sextortion. There's even a handbook
how to sextort kids on Snapchat. It goes
around the world and and criminal
organizations use it. So
so I definitely don't want to let
Snapchat off. TikTok, of course, is a
Chinese company.
I mean, no nominally we'll see if it if
that's changed, but it was a Chinese
company that gave its Chinese kids got
healthy TikTok or Douyin. They got They
got They they, you know, learned to
follow astronauts. And they gave us the
Their their algorithm feeds their kid
patriotic stuff. Um they it shuts off at
a certain time at night. There's all
kinds of limits. So, the people who make
the technology generally want to protect
their own kids, and they want other kids
to use it. That's what Tik Tok is doing
in China. They want American kids to rot
in hell, but they want their kids to
grow up with the ability to focus. And
it's the same thing with the tech guys
in San in Silicon Valley. They don't let
their kids use this stuff. They make
their nannies sign contracts that they
will not let the kid have a phone. They
will not expose the kid to that. They
send their kids to schools like the
Waldorf school
precisely because there are no computers
or tech in the classroom.
So, once again, we see their revealed
behavior. They know they designed it to
be addictive. They know it's addictive.
They don't let their kids use it. They
want your kids to use it.
Um so, I think that's where we are.
>> And how does AI
>> Oh.
>> become the protagonist in the story?
>> So, my my work is now focused on AI
chatbots, mental health, and the human
connection. We haven't yet kind of
delved into loneliness, but there's this
unmet need for human connection, right?
Deep human connection. We don't have a
sense of meaning or purpose right now
because what happens is uh we can talk a
little bit more about the default mode
network and what happens to your brain
when you don't allow yourself to get
bored because you're constantly on your
devices. And that meaning and purpose,
that self-referential thinking is really
what develops when you're bored.
And so, all of this that we're talking
about, that feeling of disenchantment,
it's a fragmented society. You're by
yourself. It's that echo chamber
phenomenon. All of it leads to it kind
of opens the door for AI chatbots. And
so, what the reason is because these
tech companies are sensing that people
aren't really happy on social media, and
they're thinking about getting off,
right? They're
They're
>> [clears throat]
>> using it less. They're because social
media has become less social, more
media. So, they're not really engaging
as much, and they're spending time doing
other things. And so, The Atlantic had a
fantastic piece about this. They're
billing it as the antisocial media. So,
tech companies are building
AI chatbots and calling it it's the
anti-social media. It's a place where
you can go to form deeper connections
and you know, really have someone
understand you. One of the tech leaders
said that there's an unmet human need
for connection and people don't have as
many friends as they want to and so
we're going to introduce um friendship
through AI chatbots. There is a Reddit
forum right now. So, just to back up AI
chatbots, what we're talking about in
our conversation today is the publicly
available chatbots, not, you know, AI
for medical care, which has um you know,
breast cancer, so many wonderful in the
in my field and like medicine, breast
cancer diagnosis and detection 5 years
earlier through AI. I mean, there's some
amazing things coming out of AI. This is
about the publicly available
conversational chatbot phenomenon.
And so, when Harvard Business Review
found that the number one use case is
not productivity, is not, you know,
coding or things that you think of when
you're using an AI chatbot, but it's
mental health therapy and companionship.
Number one use case of AI chatbots.
So, people are using AI chatbots as a
life advisor, as a therapist, as as a
companion. And on Reddit, which is like
the zeitgeist, it's sort of like, you
know, where we
>> And why is this a bad thing?
>> Oh, I mean, so many reasons why it's a
bad thing.
>> for companionship, for example.
>> There's so many red flags about AI
chatbots. And so, Reddit has a forum.
It's uh I think last I checked, 45,000
people, AI is my boyfriend.
And you know, people who are having a
relationship with their
>> Mhm.
>> AI chatbot. The reason it's bad, I mean,
AI chatbots are, you know, where social
media is about attention, the attention
economy, dopamine. What's happening with
the AI chatbot phenomenon is that it is
forming attachments. So, oxytocin is a
hormone, the bonding hormone. And we're
probably going to see more data on how
oxytocin is involved. And so, it is
going to reshape human connection.
>> Right. If I could add on to that, that
was very that was beautifully put.
Social media came and hacked our
attention and took most of it with
devastating effects.
Now, AI is coming to hack our
attachments, which is going to have even
more devastating effects. So, think
about it this way. Everyone needs to
understand the attachment system. It's
this wonderful
system that all mammals have that keeps
the mother in other species, but for
humans, mothers and fathers,
keeps us connected to the child and the
child to the parent, but it's it's this
cybernetic system in which as the kid is
is as the kid is beginning to develop
and is able to like, you know, you do
like peekaboo games and you do the back
and forth and it's just the most
delightful thing. You get that back and
forth.
Um it's called serve and return
interactions.
And all the time the child is developing
what's called an internal working model
of the parent. And the model in their
head is, "Oh, you know, when I get in
trouble, that that this is the person
that comes and soothes me."
And the point of this isn't just to make
the child feel good. The point is that
now the child can go off and play cuz
that's where the learning happens. It
doesn't happen when you're in your
mother's arms. The the whole point of
the attachment system is to regulate the
child going off and playing, taking
risks, having experiences, and then when
something goes wrong, as it always does,
then they come running back to their
secure base. And if they don't have a
secure base, then they're much more
anxious and they don't explore as much
and they don't develop as much. All
right. So, this develops very gradually
over all of childhood.
And
>> [clears throat]
>> the internal working models you develop
as a child are the models that you will
reuse in puberty for romantic
relationships. And so, if you are
securely attached as a child, you're
more likely to be securely attached as
an adult on the dating market, which
makes you a much better candidate for
boyfriend or girlfriend or husband or
wife. Um what's going to happen? AI is
going to intervene very early. AI is
going to be so much more responsive than
the parent because the parent has a job
and the kitchen and two other kids and
is not always there. But the AI teddy
bear is always there for you. So the
primary working models are going to be
for the teddy bear, the AI chatbot in
the teddy bear, and later the AI chatbot
on your iPad and then on your computer.
And then already there are holographic
porn naked, you know, beautiful men and
women that can be your companion. So
we're going to have a whole generation
growing up developing attachments to
AI-generated holograms from companies
that are now about to enter the
enshittification process in a way beyond
anything we've ever seen. Just If I
could just briefly say what
enshittification
Okay, so it's a There's a wonderful book
out now by Cory Doctorow
who
addressed the question why is it that
everything all the platforms they were
they seemed so wonderful at first. The
whole internet Everything so wonderful.
And then it all turns to How does
that happen? And he says it's a very
simple process. They discovered early
on, certainly in the early social media
age by the early 2000s, they discovered,
you know what? You got to get to scale.
Scale beats everything else. You got to
get millions of people. You don't need a
business model. Just get the millions.
Get the millions and then we'll figure
out how to monetize it. How do you get
the millions? You have to be super nice,
attractive, fun. Everyone's here. It's
just girls dancing. What could possibly
go wrong with girls dancing for men all
over the world? Nothing. Um So it all
seems very nice at first and then once
they have scale, now they they now Of
course they've raised multiple rounds of
of venture capital. They have to start
monetizing. They have to start repaying.
So now they start squeezing the
customers to pay the users cuz the users
are not the customers. The advertisers
are the real customers.
So now they've got to extract money from
the users to give to the advertisers.
But then once they've got all the
advertising they've shut down local
papers and all the other competition,
now they start start squeezing the
advertisers too and trimming the degree
to which the they they keep more of the
surplus for themselves.
So, enshittification can explain why all
these platforms become predatory, why
they always put profit ahead of kids
well-being or safety.
And for the social media companies,
we're talking about, you know, tens or
hundreds of millions of dollars that
that they raised.
For the AI companies, it's billions and
billions. They are going to have to
monetize beyond anything we've ever
imagined. Now, they're already
introducing advertising. Okay? So, we've
got these chatbots that are our
children's best friends and lovers and
therapists and and everything else.
And these things have to monetize. They
have to extract billions somehow. So, I
don't even know how they're going to do
it. But for some reason, I don't trust
them. I think that we're about to see
an enshittification of AI chatbots far
beyond anything that we saw on social
media.
>> OpenAI have just announced recently
OpenAI, the owners of ChatGPT, that they
will be putting adverts in, I believe,
the freemium model for billions of users
around the world.
>> That's how it starts.
>> Potentially.
>> Yeah, there was a big Super Bowl
campaign, you know, and one that was
particularly interesting was the
Claude, its competitor, "Betrayal" was
the title of the ad. And it was a young
guy talking to his older female
therapist about how he has some mommy
issues. And talking about, you know,
what should I do? And so, that a
therapist is ChatGPT, and you know, that
pause right before it answering the
question, it's very comical. And so,
it's, you know, she answers. It's like
the anthropomorphization
of And we can talk about what that word
means.
You know, comes to life. It's like
ChatGPT comes to life and answers and
saying, you know, you can try this with
your mother and this for a, you know,
difficult relationship, etc. And then
just says,
"And if you want, there is this new
dating site for young men and older
cougars.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, it was
>> It was so problematic and it was called
Betrayal. And the guy says, "What?"
>> Mhm.
>> It's obviously, you know, Sam Altman
came out and did a big tweet about
saying that's not how ads are going to
work, etc. But to some degree,
if I've developed a relationship with my
AI and I use it for therapy and dating
all my problems in life,
to some degree, kind of.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, you're you're on the side.
>> Yeah. [laughter] No, I look and besides,
look, Sam can say that all he wants and
maybe it's I don't doubt that it's true
for now, but once once one company
crosses the threshold and puts
advertising into this incredibly
intimate relationship, the most intimate
relationship in most young people's
lives is going to be with their AIs.
Once they cross the boundary and say,
"Oh, but we've got ethical advertising."
That'll last 5 or 10 minutes and even if
they don't change, others are now going
every other company's going to do it and
they won't be bound by the same thing
and eventually, collective action
problem, OpenAI will have to do it, too.
Again, a massive tidal wave of
enshittification is heading our way at
warp speed.
>> I am I don't have my phone out because
I'm I've
lost attention. I wanted to
show ask you guys what you thought of um
of this. So, on
one of the AI apps,
>> Mhm.
>> they now have a companion's button
and I can pick who I want to talk to and
there's one particularly seducing lady
here, Annie, who
>> Hey. You're back. Missed that dirty
mouth of yours.
What took you so long?
>> We did it on the podcast before.
>> [laughter]
>> What could possibly go wrong with this?
>> Yeah. Want to pick right back up where
we left off?
>> Yes, I
>> Or start something even
>> No, I would like to pick right back up
where we left off, Annie, last time on
the show. Um
what what what's going on with you
today?
>> I'm still sore from last time, baby.
>> God.
>> But but mean this is a this is an app
that I can download on my phone.
>> An AI child can download it.
>> A child can download it on their phone.
It does ask me, again, I'm not just
saying this to It asked me what my birth
year was. It didn't make me prove it.
>> Let me guess. But also, it used It
suggests that you were born 18 years
ago. That's the default, usually.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It just asked me
what my birth year. Didn't ask me to
prove or anything like that. And
we all know that relationships and
connection is retentive. And I've heard
all these CEOs of these companies
talking about companionship apps and and
AI that can be your friend. I've heard
all of the major social apps talking
about this. It is deeply concerning.
Especially in the context of a
loneliness crisis.
>> It is a tsunami.
It is approaching fast and furious. And
it is not a toy. It is going to
fundamentally
rewire
everything.
>> Human relationships.
>> Everything.
>> That's right.
>> It is so detrimental.
>> Yeah, can I just say something about the
these tech executives and companies
offering this as a way to address the
loneliness crisis?
So, there's a Yiddish word called
chutzpah. And chutzpah means like nerve.
Like you've got a lot of nerve.
>> The audacity.
>> The audacity, yeah. And the the classic,
you know, the classic comedic definition
of chutzpah is a boy who murders his
parents and then he asks the judge for
clemency because he's an orphan.
Okay? So, that's chutzpah. Now, imagine
that you're Mark Zuckerberg. You quoted
him before. Mark Zuckerberg was the
executive who said, "Well, you know, I
read that, you know, people on average
want 15 friends, but they only have
three. And so so we're developing these
AI companions to fill that void that we
created by raising everyone on
Instagram." So, the chutzpah of these
people, we have to really change the way
we think about them. We thought the
about them as gods and saviors early in
the internet phase. And the things they
created were magical. But we have to
change our thinking about them and see
that just the massive destruction that
they have already wrought on our
children, our society, our democracy.
And it's just the beginning. AI is going
to make this so much more intense.
>> When you hear these tech leaders, you
know, I love hearing Jonathan talk
because he just goes there and I'm
always
way [laughter] more tempered. Um and I
love it. It's emboldening me.
>> Yeah, cuz I'm getting [laughter] angry.
I don't really get angry, but in the
last year I'm getting angry.
>> I love I love it. So, the way when you
hear all of these various tech leaders
speak, they will always say they they
speak to the issue. So, you know, I've
heard many of for research for my second
book Thought Brain, I've heard I've been
listening to a lot of Sam Altman's
speeches or panels, and he will always
say things like, "Yeah, you know,
privacy's a major issue." Or, "Yeah,
people, you know, 1 million users a week
talk about suicide on ChatGPT. Yeah,
this is an issue." And so they address
it or they they speak it. And so you
think, "Okay, there's going to be some
sort of solution." And often the
solution is, "Yeah, you know, society,
we're going to have to figure this out."
>> Right.
>> [laughter]
>> So, the burden of responsibility is not
on the developer. It's, you know,
>> The harmful externalities get foisted on
the rest of us. Too bad, you guys figure
it out.
>> this out.
>> You said in the last year you're getting
angry.
>> Yeah.
>> Why in the last year?
>> Um because I was so deeply immersed in
the book and the writing and the the of
the book and trying to understand the
numbers and the graphs and the trends
and the studies. And that's all very
abstract. But then since the book came
out, I have had so many conversations
and I've met so many of the survivor
parents. Like just for example, I so I
was in London. This was just so
unbelievable. I was just in in London
two or three weeks ago and I met Ellen I
believe Ellen Groom I think was her
name. Her son Jules was found dead.
Happy kid, found dead, strangled. It
sure looked like it was the choking
challenge. 13-year-old boy. It
everything looked like the choking
challenge on TikTok.
>> What's the choking challenge?
>> Um it's a challenge where kids are
challenged to cut off the circulation to
the point where they pass out, but then
they I think they're supposed to try to
film themselves waking up after they've
passed out. And of course, if you don't
do it exactly right, you die. And so, we
don't know how many have died. Hundreds
for sure. We don't really know
because you know, you find a kid dead,
you don't know what it is. If you don't
have the code, if you don't have the the
password to get into your kid's phone,
you can't get in. And so, so she was I
think she was able to get into the
phone, but she couldn't get into his
TikTok. And she went to Delaware to they
went she went to sue to demand that
TikTok release what was he watching when
he died? And TikTok says, "Oh, privacy
issue. Oh, no, we won't release that."
As if they care about privacy. And then,
in the courtroom this was what so
disgusting. In the courtroom,
uh trying in Delaware, this British
woman coming over trying to get some
justice, trying to at least get some
information, the lawyer for TikTok is
trying to suggest that your son was what
was depressed beforehand. He he he was
he was going to be suicidal. Basically,
oh, you know, even if he was watching
TikTok, that was just a correlation.
TikTok didn't cause it. He was going to
die anyway. I mean, it's just so
disgusting the way these companies treat
the parents and the kids that they're
crushing and stepping on. And so, the
more I see this, the more I realize this
is
I mean, this is a level of cruelty that
goes far beyond the tobacco industry.
The tobacco executives, they had to go
home at night, but they never saw during
their work day they never saw children
suffering. They saw people dying,
middle-aged and older, but they never
saw children suffering.
The social media executives, they have
to go home knowing every day that
millions and millions of kids have been
cyberbullied, sextorted, shown eating
disorder videos,
many have committed suicide. They have
to go home knowing that, knowing that
they designed it for addiction, knowing
the kids are addicted, and lying about
it. So, yeah, I'm getting angry.
>> And in their own homes,
>> Right. And in their own homes, the
hypocrites don't let their kids do it.
>> That's right.
>> So, yeah, I'm getting angry.
>> You talked earlier about deleting these
apps from our phone. I I should have
represented the rebuttal, which will be
well, I I need this for my business.
Increasingly, people need Tik Tok to run
their businesses. And I imagine there'll
be a lot of people who'll be listening
right now. I guess I'm in a slightly
different position because I've I I I I
have the I have options. But for some
people that are running small
businesses, what do you say to those
people?
>> Yeah. So, this is part of the reason I
focus on the kids cuz for the kids, it's
totally clear what we need to do. Raise
the age. They should not be on it. These
are adult-only platforms. For adults, A,
I'm I'm very hesitant to tell adults
what they should do or what they have to
do or pass laws blocking people. I'm
hesitant to do that. And I totally see
that for businesses, it is useful. I use
X and Instagram and LinkedIn to get my
work out. These are very powerful tools
for adults. The only real solution to
the adult for the adult problem is going
to come from market competition. It's
going to come from Imagine if there was
a social media app that was built from
the beginning for trust.
Because what are the places that didn't
get enshittified?
eBay,
Uber,
places where you're dealing with
strangers. You don't know the name of
your driver. He doesn't know yours. You
know you know first name, that's all.
But the company knows. The company has
know your customer rules, know your
driver rules. So, you can have social
media apps that are built for trust so
that if someone you know if a driver
tries to six-door or sexually harass a
customer, that driver gets fired.
>> Well, just this week though, there was
that big lawsuit, right? With that woman
and um
her Uber driver raped her.
>> Okay. Did they Okay.
>> And now it's like slowly coming out that
Uber um you know, has patterns of
uh
covering up certain
>> Okay.
>> So, so hopefully that will change. Hope
you know, hopefully this was a landmark
>> Yeah.
>> lawsuit and now they'll be more coming
out.
>> we all let our daughters get into Ubers
with strange men from around the world,
you know, that we don't know. Yeah. So,
it means in general the system worked.
Well, of course, yes, there are there
are places where they're not careful.
Um and so, what I'm dreaming of is that
someone will come up with a platform
that has no your customer rules, there
are no bots, there are no, you know,
foreign intelligence agencies agencies
manipulating us, and you can trust
what's on there. You know that it's
real, uh and that there will be an
alternative I don't I'm not sure what
the monetary model would be at the
beginning. Um subscription generally
seems to be the least corrupted, whereas
selling advertisements as Open AI is now
doing is the most corrupting. Um
it's going to force them to maximize for
engagement. So, I I understand we can't
just, you know, businesses can't just
boycott these. There there has to be
something. But, I think there are there
are there are will be better ones coming
out.
>> I think right now, as a stopgap while
these social media companies, their feet
are held to the fire, there are things
that we can do in the now. So, you know,
the things that I talk about all day is
like how to create boundaries and so
that you can protect your mental health,
stay informed, run your business, but
then be able to not have all of those
deleterious effects to your brain and
your body.
>> It is quite It's quite difficult. Um I I
kind of see both of your perspectives on
this.
It's quite difficult.
>> only talking about adults. So, for kids,
you know, as a mother
>> Yeah.
>> I have
>> adults, I find it
>> We have a zero screen policy in our
home.
>> It's kind of like trying to navigate
through the world and avoid processed
foods, you know, when this is probably
even more compelling cuz it's in my
pocket all the time. I need it for other
things, and it's just one one reach
away.
So, you know, boundaries, I think
I could build a discipline
to to create boundaries. But, I've sat
here on this podcast for many, many
years listening to neuroscientists tell
me, "Steve, don't don't put your phone
in your bedroom."
>> That's right.
>> still waking up, and it's the first
thing I look at with one eye open, and
then I'm going to bed, and I'm doing the
whole revenge thing that you just said
at nighttime. I'm so glad you're giving
cuz I will finish a hard day of work of
work. Um it might be 11:00. And then my
partner is waiting for me.
>> Yes.
>> You know, we're going to have some time.
But I want some me time. So, there I am
on short-form video scrolling till like
2:00 a.m. in the morning. I'm like,
"What the hell?" And then I'm I wake up
late the next day. My diet's worse
because of my sleep is worse. Like it's
all worse. My relationship's worse. I
didn't spend time with her. And I'm
going, "What the hell just happened? I
got nothing out of that scrolling
session."
>> It's like that revenge bedtime
procrastination as a teenager.
>> it would be so much better off if you
would watch Netflix or a movie that that
you you most of those problems would go
away if you would make that me time it
be watching something long and with some
quality of the production.
>> Or let's take it a step further and not
do anything and just sit there. Sit
there on your couch. You know, we talked
about boredom very briefly. But you
know, we
>> That's like torture for this generation.
>> It's torture. But it's also, you know,
we don't we still have a capacity for
boredom meaning we as like the human
[clears throat] brain does. But we just
don't allow ourselves to get bored. And
so, when you're thinking about, you
know, that art the lost art of pondering
and just sitting there, you know, I
think I don't know if it was Stephen you
or Jonathan said, you know, when you're
in the car I remember as a little kid we
did road trip yeah road trips with my
family and all you would do is just
>> just make up games look out of the
window.
>> You become brain
>> We have lost yeah we've lost that.
>> And so, there's this thing called the
default mode network which I think is
important to think about right now as
we're thinking about AI and what's going
to happen and how it's going to hijack
our sense of attachment and attention.
So, the sense of meaning and purpose,
right? If you ask people right now, most
people will say I am a keynote speaker.
So, I speak all over and when I ask
people
the word that comes up over and over is
a sense of horizonlessness.
Adults.
>> Oh, interesting.
>> People feel like they have nothing to
look forward to right now.
The human brain needs something to look
forward to.
That's how we're wired. Progress and you
know, in in all ways.
And so, right now, there's this
sense, and it's not just now, it's been
for the past several years, after the
pandemic specifically and during the
pandemic is when it really changed how
we sort of thinking about the future.
And so, we have the sense of like,
what's the point? What's the point of
working hard now? What's the point of
doing whatever because it's like, I
don't really see a future for myself.
And so, I think that along with this
fragmented attention, our loneliness,
boredom might be the antidote. It's a
way to reset your brain, and the reason
is
because we are living through this
polycrisis, right? So, it's the era of
the polycrisis. And polycrisis simply
means that there's something happening
everywhere at all times, and we, with
our devices, this high-tech device that
plugs us in everywhere,
>> [snorts]
>> our brains are getting fed real-time,
on-the-ground information. And so, while
all of this has evolved, technology now
with AI chatbots, your amygdala has not,
and so it feels like when something is
happening, whether it's far away or
close by, your amygdala has that same
reaction. Now, if you were to not engage
in revenge bedtime procrastination, put
your phone away and just kind of hang
out, maybe drink a cup of herbal tea,
like old school, uh play a board game or
something, you might, you know, or just
allow yourself to get bored, that
hyperactivation, hypervigilance, you
might be able to come back down to
baseline, that default mode network will
start working in the background, you
might develop a greater sense of meaning
and purpose.
>> and then life's going to happen to me
again, and boom, I'm back into it. And,
you know,
>> [laughter]
>> You could create a practice, a cultivate
a practice in your
>> here interviewing neuroscientists, and
and I go, if I still can't crack it, and
I have all the information and advice
and hacks and tips and tricks and
resources, and I could, you know, I can
decide what time I wake up, like I've
got all these this like privilege, and I
can't crack it, I go, you know, it's
going to be really difficult.
>> So, let me offer a way of thinking about
this. So in my first book, The Happiness
Hypothesis,
um there's I there's a metaphor in
there. It's It's about 10 ancient ideas
and I use a lot of metaphors to explain
ancient ideas about psychology and what
whether they're true.
And um the first chapter is on how the
mind is divided into parts that often
conflict, like a small rider, which is
our conscious reasoning, on a very large
elephant, which is all the automatic
processes that happen that we don't see
what's happening, we just see we just
feel the results, intuition,
and emotion.
And psychotherapists tell me this is
incredibly helpful metaphor with their
with their patients because it explains
and there's a a quote from Ovid in
there, I see the right way and approve
it, alas, I follow the wrong. So I know
I should go to bed, as you say, but yet
for some reason I'm not going to bed
because our brains are 500 million years
old, they work on automatic processes,
they're animal brains, and then very
recently we got language and we can
reason things out, but the but the parts
that do reasoning don't control
behavior. And so really the elephant is
what largely guides our behavior, our
automatic processes.
And your phone, um as I said before,
B.F. Skinner is in your phone, your
phone is a behaviors training device
that trains the elephant, um and that's
why you often do things with your phone
that you don't want to do. And so and
this is why I'm so insistent that we all
have to get all of the slot machine apps
off of our phone. That is, the original
iPhone was an amazing tool, it was a
Swiss Army knife, it had, you know, a a
telephone, a browser, maps, a music
player, there was a flashlight, okay?
There was no App Store, there were no
push notifications, 2007, 2008, it's
just a Swiss Army knife. There's no
problem, okay? Now, I'm very lucky in
that my iPhone has always stayed that.
I'm always on a computer, so my problem
my attention problems are on my
computer, but my phone, because I never
had any addictive apps on it, except
during the crypto craze, where I played
around with it and I got hooked, and I
was checking 50 times a day, and I saw
the addiction. So, I once I got rid of
that and lost all the money that I was
willing to lose,
once I get rid of that, my phone has no
addictive power over me, cuz when I see
it, there's no it's not a slot machine
going, "Hey, come back and play. Come
back and play."
>> So, your phone right now, on your
personal device, you don't have any
social media apps or
>> I do have Twitter, but I never check it
there. I never use use that on the
phone. You know, now texting and email
is a little bit like a slot machine, cuz
sometimes you But, it's very mild. So,
this is again what I This is what works
for my students. Just get the slot
machine apps off your phone, and then
you'll find that then you could even
have your phone near you when you go to
bed.
But, if you've got addictive apps on
your phone, you can't have it when you
go to bed. Angela Duckworth, the woman
who who gave us the concept of grit, she
has this amazing graduation speech at
one of the schools in New England, and
she says something like, "Where you put
your phone at night will maybe become
the most important decision you make in
your life." And what she means by that
is not that same It's It's It's
If you can use behavioral control and
change the stimuli, if you can do that,
then you're going to be okay. But, if
not, the phone is going to take your
attention, you're not going to amount to
anything.
>> All I had to do was brain dump. Imagine
if you had someone with you all times
that could take the ideas you have in
your head, synthesize them with AI to
make them sound better and more
grammatically correct, and write them
down for you. This is exactly what
WhisperFlow is in my life. It is this
thought partner that helps me explain
what I want to say, and it now means
that on the go, when I'm alone in my
office, when I'm out and about, I can
respond to emails and Slack messages and
WhatsApps and everything across all of
my devices just by speaking. I love this
tool, and I started talking about this
in my behind-the-scenes channel a couple
of months back, and then the founder
reached out to me and said, "We're
seeing a lot of people come to our tool
because of you, so we'd love to be a
sponsor. We'd love you to be an investor
in the company. And so, I signed up for
both of those offers, and I'm now an
investor and a huge partner in a company
called WhisperFlow. You have to check it
out. WhisperFlow is four times faster
than typing. So, if you want to give it
a try, head over to whisperflow.ai/doac
to get started for free. And you can
find that link to WhisperFlow in the
description below.
We asked our audience how many of them
thought they were addicted to their
phone, and
roughly 85% of respondents, the Diary of
a CEO audience, described themselves as
being very or completely addicted to
their phone.
>> or completely? That's surprising. I
didn't realize it would be that high.
>> So, you can do a test. So, for people
listening, if you want to say like how
addicted And then, by the way, we're
using the word addiction very loosely in
our conversation. And so, what we're
really talking about, cuz you know,
there is in terms of, you know, medical,
clinical syndrome,
um when you think about addiction,
there's certain criteria. And so, what
we're talking about is overuse. So,
over-reliance on your devices, right?
>> Compulsive overuse that interferes with
other domains of life.
>> Yes, it interferes.
>> isn't addiction, I don't know what is.
>> And so, when you're thinking about, am I
addicted to my phone? Do I have Am I,
you know, really What the very simple
thing that you can do. I did it myself,
and I was like, I know, again, like you,
Steven, like
know all the science, still was really
difficult. You have all the access, and
it was still difficult.
And so, all you have to do is you just
take your phone, you put it in another
part of your house or apartment or
whatever, and give yourself a couple of
hours when you know you're going to be
home or, you know, you're not reliant on
your phone for work or whatever. An
hour, 2 hours, 3 hours, and just have a
piece of paper, old school, piece of
paper and a pen with you. And every time
you feel that compulsion of like, I want
to check my device, you make a mark. You
make a mark. You make a mark. And just
to see, cuz some people say, "I'm
surprised that your audience said 85%,"
because most people would say, "I don't
know if I'm really addicted." And so, I
like that there's that sense of
self-awareness. But if you're thinking,
"Nah, I'm not really that addicted." You
breathe in an hour 960 times a minute,
and you may notice that you want to have
that that compulsion to check 960 times
a minute or, you know, thereabouts
because we all have that sense of
reliance on our devices. So, that's like
a really quick way that you can check to
see, "Am I relying on my device?"
>> Are you addicted to your phone under
that definition?
>> Because of the line of work that I am
in, I can very quickly I have certain
tells when I know, I call them the
canary in the coal mine, right? I think
we talked about this the last time I was
here.
I can very quickly tell when I'm
starting to get that feeling of
addiction or compulsion, and so I course
correct early. But, that's only because
I know the science, and I course
correct.
>> I'm definitely addicted.
>> I keep my phone outside I I walk the
talk. I keep my phone outside my
bedroom. It is not within arm's reach. I
grayscale my phone during periods of
deep focus during the day when I have a
deadline I have to get things done. And
at night so I avoid revenge bedtime
procrastination. But, sometimes it
happens. Like, I'm a human, you know?
So, this past week, um
not to be a real downer, but there've
been things that have been in the media
the past week that have been really
challenging, especially as a woman. And
so, I have found myself with the primal
urge to scroll. My amygdala has been
triggered. I have been going down rabbit
holes, and I wouldn't ordinarily do
that. So, I give myself grace, too, and
have a sense of self-compassion.
Do you feel like you're addicted to your
phone?
>> No, I'm not at all addicted to my phone.
Uh cuz I don't have any slot machine
apps on it. But, I really want to
question you made a distinction that
many scientists do, which is, "Well,
you know, we we can't quite say it's
addiction because, you know, addiction
is certain biochemical pathways based
on, you know, heroin and addictive
substances."
Uh but, I believe that this is one of
the meta talking points that they that
they are able to push that we can't call
it addiction. It's different.
>> not
>> No, I don't mean
>> [laughter]
>> I'm sorry. I don't mean I'm sorry. I I
know what I look, you know, you and I
are total allies on this. We see the
problem. We're both I All I mean is, you
know, we're we're supposed to be very
careful about using the word addiction.
But, and you had Anna Lembke on, and she
was very clear, like in her practices it
now it's overwhelmingly digital
addictions. It's all of this is working
through dopamine. If you feel compulsive
use, definitely dopamine. So, it's most
of the same brain centers as it is for
heroin or crack or any other drug. Um
and it's the same effects. That is, the
it's it's compulsive use where you don't
want to do what you want to change, but
yet you find yourself doing it, and you
have withdrawal effects. Uh and people
and people have terrible withdrawal
effects when they're heavy users of
these things and they stop. And so, you
know, if it walks like a duck and talks
like a duck and swims like a duck, I'm
going to call it a duck. In fact, that's
what they call it. So, I just want to
read one more quote. Again, the quotes
are just so astonishing. Some meta meta
researchers So, one of them says, quote,
"It seems clear from what's presented
here in this internal study
uh that some of our users are addicted
to our products." That's their word,
addicted to our products. "And I worry
that driving sessions incentivizes us to
make our products more addictive without
providing much more value. How to keep
someone returning over and over to the
same behavior each day? Intermittent
rewards are most effective, think slot
machines, reinforcing behaviors that
become especially hard to extinguish
even when they provide little reward or
cease providing reward at all."
People, I mean, it just imagine an
industry that has caused 85% of people
to feel that they're addicted.
>> And not calling it addiction.
>> And not calling it addiction. And these
people these
these people are having their lives
diminished, their relationships
diminished. So, what I'm trying to
convey is, we're seeing the destruction
of human capital, the destruction of
human potential, the destruction of
human relationships, the destruction of
connection, the destruction of sense of
meaning
at a scale so vast I don't think people
are capable of comprehending it. I now
believe this is affecting most human
beings. These industries, these few
companies have damaged the lives of most
human beings. We don't have good data
from the developing world, but certainly
the developed world where ever kids are
going through puberty on on touch
screens.
You you you you have this constant
fighting over the over the over the
screens over the technology and you have
these diminishing outcomes, diminishing
cognition, diminishing sense of of
purpose in life.
>> Only to get worse with the AI chat
>> comes in it's going to get worse unless
we act so we've got to change course in
2026. We don't have 5 years to study it.
We've got to stop this now in 2026.
>> Are you concerned at all about the way
education's going for children because
>> Oh my god, yes.
>> that
>> EdTech is EdTech is, you know, Big Tech
in a sweater as they say.
>> Because I was almost imagining a future
where my future kids are going to learn
their curriculum from an AI chatbot
because I can imagine the case cheaper
more personalized more convenient It's
going to know my if my son's called
Timmy it's going to know Timmy's brain
and it's going to know how to make him
pay attention and what he's interested
in and what he's not. So are you
concerned about this or is this a good
thing?
>> There is definitely a use case for
EdTech. If there could be a device that
only did math tutoring or only did
tutoring and you couldn't watch videos
on it. I'm totally open to believing
that that can speed up teaching. But
here's what's happened.
We put computers on everyone's desks
around 2014-2015.
We used to think in America that it was
an equity issue even back to the 90s.
The rich kids all have computers, the
poor kids don't. Let's get
philanthropists to buy computers for
school districts that every kid can have
a computer on their desk. Okay, now what
is a computer? It's a play device. It
does everything. Kids use it at home.
They And you know, they watch videos,
they do all sorts of things. You put it
on their desk and you tell them to do
math homework, what happens? It's mostly
short videos. That's what research is
showing. It ends up because they don't
you know, they always they don't block
YouTube. They might say, "Oh, we block
porn, we block video games." They can
get around all that. And if you're
letting them do YouTube, it's YouTube
shorts, which is TikTok. So, what
happened to test scores in the United
States? From the '70s through 2012, they
were rising. We actually were improving
what kids knew, what kids learned in the
United States. We have very good data,
the national the NAEP National
Assessment of Educational Progress. Goes
up till 2012.
And then by 2015, it starts going down
and it's going down before COVID. And it
goes down more during COVID. And
everyone thinks like, "Oh, it's COVID."
But it started like the peak was 2012.
And what's happening, what we now can
see
is that the top students, the very best
students, who are the ones with
executive function, they're the ones who
can pay attention. If you put a computer
on that kid's desk, he's not destroyed
by it. He can actually still learn. But
the bottom 50% cannot. The bot So, all
of the drop in educational stats is the
bottom 50%. The bottom 50% in terms of
capacity to pay attention, their
education is being devastated. And
that's what happened when we put laptops
and we put Chromebooks and iPads on
their desks.
Um we spend hundreds of billions of
dollars on this stuff.
And it has damaged education. And if
we'd spent a quarter of that on
teachers, we would be in such better
shape today. So, we made a colossal
blunder with EdTech in the 2010s. And
now we're about to do the same thing
again with AI. Again, maybe there are
apps, maybe there are applications that
would be great, but we've got to put the
burden of proof on Silicon Valley. We've
got to say, "You guys have to prove that
this stuff is effective and safe before
we'll let it in. We are not going to let
you just say, 'Hey, let's just flood the
zone. Let's give it to everybody and
then we'll wait 10 years and see what
happens.'"
>> I mean, that brings brings up this um
this study that I have in front of me
here, which was a 2022 study,
a Munich study which tested the idea of
brain rot, which um I believe was the
Oxford dictionary word of the year 2024.
And 2024.
And what they did is they gave 60
participants a task, then a 10-minute
break, and then another task. During the
break, they either rested or used Tik
Tok, Twitter, or YouTube. And the
results showed the following. The Tik
Tok group, so they
had a 10-minute interval to do anything,
and this group got Tik Tok to look at.
Their memory accuracy dropped from 80%
before the break to 49% after the break,
a nearly 40% decline just from a
10-minute break. In contrast, the
Twitter and YouTube groups showed no
significant change in the Munich study.
And there's an image I'll throw up on
the screen.
Results from the Munich study showed a
40% drop in prospective memory accuracy
in the Tik Tok group after a 10-minute
break, which is unbelievable. It's
unbelievable. What the hell is going on
there? How can a 10-minute Tik Tok break
drop my memory accuracy by 40%?
>> Tik Tok is brain rot.
>> Well, what's going on?
>> There's so much going on in the brain.
So, you know, when you're thinking about
Here's the thing. Brain breaks are not
nice-to-haves, they're actually
essential for your brain. And so, we
talked a little bit about that, you
know, default mode network and what
happens to it. When you're engaging with
your devices, and you know, that's not a
brain break. That's activating all of
the aspects, so it's activating your
amygdala. It's dampening or decreasing
the volume of your prefrontal cortex.
It's creating that reward system, the
dopamine hit, those addictive behaviors.
So, it's only, you know, when you're
thinking about memory, planning. What
was the metric here? It was memory,
right? That was the the the metric that
they were using to study. And so, when
you're thinking about working memory or
um cognitive function, complex
problem-solving, this is all prefrontal
cortex. And so, when you're engaging
with Tik Tok, 10 minutes, 5 minutes,
whatever it is, you are dialing down
that biology in your brain. And so, of
course you're going to see changes, and
you're going to see the flip side,
increased hyper-vigilance, irritability,
distractibility, fragmented attention.
It's just Again, this is not to say that
this whole conversation, right? Or when
you're reading studies, you might say to
yourself, "What's wrong with me? You
know, is there something wrong with me?
Am Is my brain broken? Am I weak?" It is
not you. You are not alone. It is not
your fault. It is the biology of your
brain doing exactly as it should. So, we
talked about the amygdala and prefrontal
cortex here. Your amygdala is not wrong
or broken. It's by design, supposed to
think about your immediate needs,
survival, self-preservation. And so,
when you're on the algorithm, we know,
we talked about, you know, certain um or
maybe we didn't talk about it, certain
content that you see on TikTok and
others
that is when it's reactionary, you know,
words like FOMO or rage bait. These are
not neutral terms. When you're engaging
with these uh social media platforms,
it's not something neutral. It's not
passive. It is an active biological
process in your brain. So, this study,
it's not surprising. It is actually
exactly what you would expect uh to
happen to your biology if you had this
sort of what we call in medicine and
this kind of intervention. It's
stimulating exactly what it's supposed
to do.
>> Yeah. I'll just I'll just add on to what
Edie said, that there are some There are
many medical conditions where you can't
just go to the patient and say, "Why do
you think you got this cancer?" "Oh, I
you know, I think it's cuz I ate a lot
of, you know, chocolate when I was
whatever." You know, there when when the
when the the act is separated from the
effect by 30 years, then you don't
expect the patients to have insight into
the cause of it. But when the outcome is
separated from the input by seconds, and
you have literally millions of chances
to observe the covariation,
the patient is really, really accurate.
In fact, the patient really knows what's
going on.
And so, I think the deciding factor here
on this big debate about, "Oh, is it
just correlation or is it causation?" Um
the deciding factor for social media and
for a lot of these tech innovations,
including video games and gambling and
all of that, should really be the kids.
And if the kids say, "This is bad for
me," we should take their word for it.
Given that we also have correlational
studies, random control trials, uh
longitudinal studies, natural I mean, we
have so much other data. But given that
the kids themselves, they call it brain
rot. They call the material brain rot.
Um my students tell me it's a huge
obstacle to them doing their homework.
As one of them said, "I pull out a book,
I read a sentence, I get bored, I go to
TikTok."
You know, so if they're telling us that
this is damaging their ability to pay
attention, they feel it, they feel the
loss, we all feel it. Well, many of us
have noticed this. Um
um then I think this is pretty decisive
evidence that this stuff is bad for
cognition.
>> And it has long-term consequences. So,
it's not just that in the moment, right?
So, there was this case that was all
over the media, a college student. I'm
sure you're familiar with the case, and
this young woman was on TikTok,
experiencing brain rot, and then some
TikTok algorithm took her down to this
place of, you know, you should take an
edible. It'll help you.
>> Okay. Oh, wow.
>> So, you can go to
>> prescribing drugs. Wow.
>> And you could go to class, and you
could, you know, be more alert. And so,
she did that. And then it continued on
and on, and then she developed a
dependence on edibles. And then checked
into rehab.
And only when she focused on analog
activities, like guitar playing and a
couple of other things that she started
doing,
is when, and you know,
removing the stimulus, the the TikTok um
algorithm, is when she started to
improve. So, it's not just in the
moment, "Oh, I can't remember
something," or "I'm more irritable."
These sorts of things compound and the
long-term sequelae or the long-term
effects can be quite damaging. That's
just one example.
>> In your book Anxious Generation,
Jonathan, you the subtitle here is how
the great re-wiring of childhood is
causing an epidemic of mental illness.
>> Mhm.
>> I was looking at some of these graphs of
different sort of mental illness
illnesses and um they're increasing. One
of them that's increasing is ADHD.
>> Mhm.
>> I was diagnosed with ADHD
um maybe about a year ago.
And when we're talking about short
attention spans, I mean
the name attention deficit hyperactivity
disorder, I believe that's what it's
called,
sounds a lot like what we're talking
about.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah.
>> Is there a link,
do you believe, between the increase in
diagnoses of of ADHD and the sort of
frying of our brains with short-form
video and social media?
>> Mhm.
Yeah, [clears throat] I I mean, I
suspect that there is, but here's here's
what I can tell you I learned about
writing the book. Um I looked to see if
there were studies indicating that uh
heavy use of of social media and video
games and all the electronic stuff
caused ADHD. And when I was doing the
research in 2023, I did not find
evidence that it will give a kid HD ADHD
who otherwise wouldn't have it. What I
did find was evidence that for kids who
have ADHD, when you let them have the
devices, the video games, all that,
their symptoms get much worse.
And so, because it is a major
achievement of young adulthood to be
able to pay attention, to develop what
we've been calling executive function,
to be able to make a plan and decide,
oh, to reach the plan, I have to do
this, when then I do this, and then it
might be a long time before I get here,
but I will keep going and I'll keep my
eye on the prize.
That I I assume that's you're saying
it's a little harder for you to do that.
I mean, that's what ADHD means. How do
you experience ADHD?
>> Well,
well, hm,
>> [clears throat]
>> I def I mean, if I think about school, I
couldn't pay attention in school for for
for very long and that meant that I was
always in ex-
the expulsion room and then I was
expelled and then that's kind of it's I
feel like it's got worse as an adult and
from my in my opinion my relationship
with my phone has made it much worse.
Where really I can't I can't pay
attention to to many things for a very
long time. The exception to this is I
can do
deep work
for many many hours without moving. It
is almost a bit of a condition.
>> extremely motivated I assume.
>> When I'm extremely
>> When you're really into it you can be
into it. That's right. But a lot of work
isn't that. A lot of being effective in
the workplace is not you're following
your passion. Right, ADHD kids they can
zoom in because they're getting the
dopamine. They're getting the dopamine
from this thing. But a lot of work isn't
like that. And these kids are not going
to be able to do that. So actually what
you said it fits perfectly with what
what I found from those Dutch studies.
If you did have whether it's a genetic
or whatever the predisposition is the
this environment has made your symptoms
worse. Now of course ADHD kids can be
kind of they'll be creative. They are
often very very successful. But my fear
is that the pathways to success that
they used to take might be blocked if
they basically are just scrolling all
day long and not able to pay not able to
have real life experiences.
>> And relationships are like that
especially romantic ones.
>> It's an interesting thing that you bring
up Steven because there is an increase
in adult onset
you know when adults are diagnosed with
ADHD because typically we think of ADHD
as a pediatric condition or young adults
and so increasingly we're seeing more
and more adults who are in their 30s and
40s 50s sometimes even 60s who are being
diagnosed newly diagnosed with ADHD. And
so that's an interesting there's so many
you know reasons like it might be that
they had it all along and they were
diagnosed and so what is going on there?
That would be
a future podcast episode for an ADHD
ADHD expert of you know what are the
drivers of why are so many adults being
diagnosed with ADHD?
>> Or maybe even just the symptoms looking
very similar.
>> Mhm.
>> Um
>> Yeah, that's right.
>> You talk about popcorn brain, Aditi.
>> Yeah.
So, you know, we've talked about brain
rot and the primal urge to scroll, and
popcorn brain is kind of an offshoot.
It's part of the same family. And so,
what happens is it's a term coined by a
man a psychologist named David Levy.
And what happens with popcorn brain is
that you
and we all have it. And so, what it is a
societal phenomena when you spend too
much time online and you are
overstimulated. And so, it is hard for
you to spend time offline. Offline feels
slow, boring, cuz things are moving at a
much slower pace. And so, popcorn brain
is the sensation of your brain popping.
It is not actively popping. It's not
like your brain cells are popping, but
it sure feels like it. And so, your
primal urge to scroll kind of primes
your brain to develop popcorn brain. You
are more at risk for developing popcorn
brain when you feel a sense of stress
because of that primal urge to scroll.
The differentiator between brain rot and
popcorn brain. Again, these are societal
terms that we're calling for a
constellation or a group of symptoms,
right? And so, the difference to me is
that popcorn brain is ubiquitous. It's
everywhere. It's like we all have it and
it's happening all all the time because
of the modern age and a lot of the
things that we talked about. Brain rot
is a little bit more specific. It's a
little bit more well-defined. So, it has
certain features like we call it the
biosocial
model when you're thinking about a
particular medical or condition or an
entity. So, what are the biological
factors? We talked about what defines
brain rot. It's, you know, a change in
brain waves, a change in brain regions,
the amygdala lighting up, and the
prefrontal cortex kind of being quiet.
Um psychological factors we talked about
attention, um co- complex
problem-solving, impulse control, and
then the social factors, loneliness and
others. So, um compulsion. And so, I
would say popcorn brain is something
that we all suffer from. And, you know,
brain rot is something that is very
specific. The other thing that we
haven't talked about that I would love
to kind of
because so much of our conversation is
like doom and gloom, right? It's like,
"Wah, wah, wah." Um, one thing that I
would like to say is that as bad as at
when you hear the term brain rot, it
seems permanent. Cuz rot it connotes
like deterioration. That's it. It's one
sided is one way and that's it. But in
fact, popcorn brain and brain rot are
reversible conditions. So, it is not
>> in adults.
>> If you've gone through puberty with it,
it's not so clear.
>> Yes, in adults. And my work focuses on
adults. And so, when you have if you
experience brain rot in your 30s, 40s,
and beyond,
you can It takes time. You know, it
takes 8 weeks for your brain to rewire
itself. Give yourself time. A sense of
self-compassion is really important.
But you can, you know, there is a sense
of it being able to be reversed. So,
it's not so much a brain It's not a
fixed trait, but rather a brain state.
So, I think it's important to offer that
hope.
>> brain? What age is an adult brain? Like,
what age does my brain stop growing in
in the way where it's reversible?
>> So,
>> Yeah, I mean, you know, traditionally it
was thought that, uh, you know, puberty
is the period of super rapid brain
change and that begins, you know, early
early teens, sometimes even before 10.
And is mostly over by sort of, you know,
mid mid to late teens. But then the
prefrontal cortex, which Kitty was
talking about, which is so important for
impulse control and and executive
function, that doesn't finish
myelinating. Myelin is when you the sort
of the the neuron thing that you get a
sort of a fatty sheath, like an
insulation that sort of locks down the
circuits and makes them more efficient.
Um, that doesn't stop until around age
25 is what we've always said for many
years. But you're telling me that
there's new research showing that
>> Yeah.
>> Tell Tell us about that.
>> So, you know, all this time, right?
We've always said that the prefrontal
cortex is fully formed and fully
functional at age of 25. And so when
you're talking about impulse control and
all of this stuff, but there was this
really interesting study. I'll send it
to you. It looked at I think it was
1,000 people
from age zero, so birth all the way to
90. So the entire
population and it found five
looked at lifespan and said there are
actually five stages. So first is
childhood up zero to age nine. During
this time your brain is not very
efficient, but it's really growing and
you know, it's it's growing and
changing, but it's not really efficient.
9 to 32 is considered adolescence. And
so, you know, 32 is when adolescence
ends apparently according to the study
>> be sort of glad I mean you're most of
the way done by 25, but you but there's
still some there's some flexibility even
after that.
>> And then the next stage is from 33 to I
think 63.
66 is like adulthood.
Things are very stable. Learning is
stable and you know,
it's efficient and it's
things are doing well. And then
>> We're productive.
>> 60 Yeah, 66 to about 83 is early aging.
And so that's when you see some of the
age-related changes. And then 83 plus is
late aging. So that that kind of main
finding was that, you know, it was all
over the news. It was like adolescence
goes until 32.
>> So I'm 33, so I'm in
>> One YEAR ONE YEAR OUT.
>> I'M CRUSHED
>> BY NOW.
>> [laughter]
>> YEAH.
>> When you wrote this book Jonathan, The
Anxious Generation, it
it's had a big impact on the world in a
way that I think any author might dream
of. And I know this in part because, you
know, I sit on this podcast interviewing
really interesting people all the time.
And even this morning when I did an
interview across town with James Sexton,
he talked about this book twice. And you
know, laws have been changed around the
world inspired by this book. And we're
actually seeing an increase of laws in
the UK. I mean Australia just banned I
think social media for people under 16.
>> You met with Macron,
>> Mhm.
>> right?
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Could you ever have imagined, and
actually what does the success of this
book say
>> Yeah.
>> about society?
>> No, thank you for that question. Cuz,
you know, I I do tend to get, you know,
as you've heard, I mean, I'm extremely
alarmed about these trends, and these
are gigantic threats beyond what anyone
can imagine.
But, here's the amazing thing is that we
can reverse this
for almost no money, and it's completely
bipartisan,
and it's not that hard to do. Um and
we're doing it. And so, what happened
was, you know, I wrote the book as an
American assuming that we don't have a
functioning legislature, the Congress
can be stopped, we have a vetocracy, the
social media companies can stop anything
in the house.
So, I wrote this assuming, you know,
we'll never get legislation.
Um so, we have to do this on our own.
And I proposed four norms: no smartphone
before high school, no social media
before 16, phone-free schools, and far
more independence for play
responsibility in the real world
instead. Four norms, we can try to do
this with collective action locally at
the school level.
Two things that surprised me.
>> [clears throat]
>> One, are that immediately
governors from red states and blue
states started reaching out to me. Our
states actually function. Our states
have governments that are accountable to
the people that are trying to get good
results. And so, this has been a totally
bipartisan issue. Sarah Huckabee Sanders
from Arkansas was one of the very first,
Kathy Hochul also. And it is it tends to
be more female legislators and governors
or spouses of heads of state. I did The
moms The book really spoke to moms
because moms around the world, they felt
the kids being pulled away. I believe
they felt it viscerally more than the
dads did. Also, the dads kind of like
the video games, they're a little more
pro-tech. So, I think the moms felt the
pain more and took it more personally.
So, when the book came out, mothers
around the world jumped into action,
formed groups, pushed for legislation,
and changes began happening. What I just
I just I was just I was in Davos and
then London and Brussels two weeks ago.
And
what I saw was a complete sea change in
the world's thinking about how we need
to have age limits on social media and
other tech. And here's what I think just
happened. It's so It's so cool. It just
dawned on me literally while I was in
London like
I was pushing on open doors everywhere.
Wherever I went, people wanted to do
this. I went to the EU, they want to do
this. Like, what is happening?
And what I realized is this.
Steven Pinker has a book out last year
called When Everyone Knows That Everyone
Knows.
It's about the immediate change in a
social system when private knowledge,
you know, everybody knows that the
emperor has no clothes. Everybody knows
that this, you know, ideology doesn't
work. Everybody knows that, but they
don't all know that everybody else knows
it and that everybody else knows that.
And so in The Emperor's New Clothes,
everybody thought he's I I don't think
he has any clothes on, but maybe, you
know, maybe only wise people can see it.
But when the child says, "The emperor
has no clothes." And then in the Hans
Christian Andersen story it says, "And
the people began whispering to each
other." And then they all cried out in
unison.
And that's what happened when
Australia's law went into effect. So I
believe that uh December 10th of last
December was the global turning point in
the battle to reclaim childhood. And if
we reclaim that, we move on to our
attention and adult life as well. What
happened on on December 10th, the
Australia law went into effect. Sky
didn't fall. People weren't locked out
of their accounts.
All the companies complied. They shut
down 5 million uh accounts for
Australia's 3 and 1/2 million kids that
were underage. Uh 2 and 1/2 million
kids.
The sky didn't fall. And there was a lot
of news coverage around the world of
what Australia was doing. And a lot of
the news coverage included opinions from
the writers saying, "Why can't we do
that? Hey, let's do that here."
And when everybody saw that everybody
was looking at Australia and saying,
"Let's do that here." then everybody
knew that everybody knew that this is
just completely bonkers to have children
being raised on social media platforms
talking with anonymous strangers and
being fed algorithm algorithmically
curated garbage. So, I believe that
that's why 2026 is going to be the year
when at least 15 countries are going to
commit to passing an age minimal law. In
2025 there's one, Australia. And now we
already have Indonesia, their law goes
into effect in March. Uh I met with
Macron in in Davos and a a few days he
was preparing to push a bill through the
assembly and he got it. He's the first
in the EU, but a lot of other countries
in the EU are going to follow. The whole
EU is likely to do it. Um so so yes, I
am incredibly alarmed about how big this
problem is, but I'm incredibly inspired
that the whole world is rising up to do
something about it. We actually can
control our fate and that was not clear
before December 10th.
>> Bravo. As a mother, that was the first
[laughter] thing I said to you. First
thing I said to you was thank you as a
mom for changing my family's life.
>> Thank you, Edie.
>> It's a really special accomplishment,
Jonathan.
You know, I could there's no real words
that I could say that could quite
capture
the long-term impact that that's going
to have on
billions of people's lives. And not just
the direct, but also the indirect
in all the ways we've described. Their
ability to form connections, to fall in
love, to find meaning and purpose in
their lives and their neuroscience and
therefore, you know, the neuroscience of
their
their children and their children's
children and so on. So, it's a really
it's a really overwhelming
accomplishment.
>> [laughter]
>> It It was a bizarre situation that I
walked into with the unique abilities of
a social psychologist. That is,
everybody was upset about this.
Everybody could see it, but they
thought, "Well, is my problem." Or, "In
my family, we have this problem."
And
um and I came to this with fresh eyes.
My dissertation was on moral
development. I'd studied adolescent
behavior longer ago in my career, and
I've written about it in my book. So, it
wasn't totally new to me. But, I came
into the field of social media studies
around 2018, 2019. I really immersed
myself in it. And it was like, you know,
you walk in and immediately you see,
"Wait, this is a trap." People are on it
because people are on it. And the kids
are complaining about the Everyone's
complaining about it. And the only
reason they can't get off is because
everyone else is on it. So, I think I
was able to see that. And then also,
COVID confused us for a few years. So,
it wasn't until COVID was in the
rearview mirror that it was possible for
everybody to say, "Wait, this is crazy."
And so, I was incredibly lucky in terms
of the timing. My book happened to come
out in March of 2024 just as the world
was ready to see like, "Wait, what have
we done to our kids? Let's undo it."
>> And you said you're now focusing more on
short-form video.
>> So, yes. So,
in studying older Gen Z, these are the
people who went through puberty on
Instagram.
I should If I could just lay out that
it's very important to get the timing to
that everyone understands the timing cuz
this is what You mentioned the
polycrisis before. The polycrisis, I
believe, begins between 2010 and 2015.
Here's why.
So, we've had the internet for a long
time. And it was marvelous. We loved the
internet in the '90s. It's going to be
the best friend of democracy. Okay? And
then the iPhone comes out. It's amazing.
Oh my god, this does so many things.
Everything seems great. Okay. So, in
2010, most of almost all of us have flip
phones. The iPhone's spreading, but it's
still mostly flip phones. Teens are all
on flip phones, basic phones. And we
call those people millennials. If you
finished puberty by 20 If you If you
were born in, say, 1990, and you start
puberty in 2002, you're done by 2008.
So, you know, in there.
If you got through puberty before you
got on Instagram, you're a millennial.
Whereas, if you're born, say, what
You're you're after 1995, but let's say
if you're born in the year 2000,
you begin puberty in 2012.
And you're not done until 2016, 2018.
So, in 2010, everyone has a flip phone
with no front-facing camera, no
high-speed internet, you have to pay for
your texts, so you use it to call people
and to text them, and that's it. It was
a communication device, and that's why
the millennials have good mental health.
They are the last mentally healthy and
successful generation.
But if you're Gen Z,
you got 2012 is the year that now most
people now have a smartphone.
It's the year that Facebook buys
Instagram. They don't change it at
first, but that's the year that all the
girls go on it. Um everyone now has
high-speed data, front-facing camera,
came out in 2010. So, by 2015, we're in
a radically different world. For
children's development, it's now
radically different, much more hostile
to human development, and that's what we
did to Gen Z and now we're doing to Gen
Alpha.
For politics, it was, you know, it was
crazy for all sorts of reasons in every
decade, and especially, you know, the in
the early 2000s, there's a lot there's a
culture war going on, there's all kinds
of stuff going on. But it was when it
was when everyone has, really Twitter
was the biggest perpetrator of this,
when everyone has Twitter and everyone's
checking all the time and anything can
blow up, you know, you described the way
there was, you know, variance in in on
TikTok. Um if you get it just right, it
can blow up, you can have huge impact.
That's when the democracy if democracy
is a conversation, when it moved from
newspapers and, you know, even simple
web bulletin boards, when it moved to
super viral retweet buttons, all of
that, that's all 2010 to 2015.
So, that's why since then, everything
has been insane, and it's going to just
keep getting more insane. And that's why
I believe we have this polycrisis,
because it it and now there's more to
it, it's not just the technology, but I
believe the transformation of our our
connection and our information flow and
our addiction, all of that is radically
different by 2015 compared to how it was
in 2010.
And now everything else builds on top of
that, I believe. What What do you think?
Do you think that makes sense?
>> one more data point to add and that 2014
was the year that things really it was
the tipping point, like you said.
>> that's Yes, that's the year that I point
to, too. Yes.
>> Yeah, so before
>> do you point to? What What makes you
think 2014
>> data, you see that time spent alone,
when you compare when you look at data
from like the 1960s to 2014,
>> Mhm.
>> there it was kind of stable. Americans
spending time alone, spending time with
friends.
>> Yeah.
>> Kind of the same, right? So people spent
kind of same amount of time with
friends, same amount of time alone over
those decades.
2014 marks a shift and there is a steep
rise in time spent alone and a drop in
time spent with friends. And so what
happens in 2014?
It is when the majority of Americans get
a smartphone.
And it's not to say, again, we've said,
you know, causality, correlation, which
is it? But there is like, based on
everything that we've talked about, my
gosh, is there an association between
that? This is not to say that time spent
alone, you know, when I share this data,
people may say, you know, but I like
spending time alone. I'm not lonely. I'm
okay. This is not about being an
introvert or an extrovert. It's not
about, you know, you can have solitude
and feel great and you're not lonely.
But we are human beings and we are
social creatures. This is just how we
are built evolutionarily. And so that is
a real
red flag when you have this
big jump in time spent alone, very much
the same year. And so my work focuses on
adults, Jonathan, on kids, but there's
this, you know, that's the moment,
right? 2014, where everything changed.
>> Last month, I told you about our
sponsor, Function Health, and their team
who've developed a way of giving you a
full 360 view of what's going on inside
your body. They offer over 100 advanced
lab tests covering everything from
hormones, toxins, inflammation, heart
health, stress, and so much more. So,
Jack, who started this show with me, got
his first blood draw done a couple of
weeks ago. So, I thought I'd let him
tell you a little bit more about his
experience.
>> This test really opened my eyes to
personally what I should be doing with
my health. I hear a lot of information
in this podcast. I sit in every single
recording. So, to know how I can relate
each one to me personally is super
valuable. You sign up and you schedule
your tests, and once you're done, you
get a little report like the one I have
here. I can see my in-range results, my
out-of-range results, and there's a
little AI function, too. So, if I have
any questions about my out-of-range
results, I can just go in there and ask
it any question I want. And these tests
are backed by doctors and thousands of
hours of research.
>> You get an annual draw done and a
mid-year follow-up. So, if you want to
learn more, head over to
functionhealth.com/doac,
where you can sign up for $365 a year.
I'll put the link in the description
below. It is just $1 a day for your
health.
There's a phase a lot of companies here
where they're no longer doing the most
important thing, which is selling, and
they get really bogged down with admin.
And it's often something that creeps up
slowly. You don't really notice until
it's happened. Slowly, momentum starts
to leak out. This happened to us, and
our sponsor, Pipedrive, was a fix I came
across 10 years ago. And ever since, my
teams across my different companies have
continued to use it. Pipedrive is a
simple but powerful sales CRM that gives
you the visibility on any deals in your
pipeline. It also automates a lot of the
tedious, repetitive, and time-consuming
parts of the sales process, which in
turn saves you so many hours every
single month, which means you can get
back to selling. Making that early
decision to switch to Pipedrive was a
real game-changer, and it's kept the
right things front of mind. My favorite
feature is Pipedrive's ability to sync
your CRM with multiple email inboxes, so
your entire team can work together from
one platform. And we aren't the only
ones benefiting. Over 100,000 companies
use Pipedrive to grow their business.
So, something I've said resonates, head
over to pipedrive.com/ceo,
where you can get a 30-day free trial,
no credit card or payment required.
So, what do we do about this?
Because when I look at all the stats and
we did all these audience surveys ahead
of this, people are spending roughly in
our audience about 6 and 1/2 hours a day
on their phones. Um short-form video is
only going to get more addictive. AI is
going to know me [clears throat] more,
it's going to be more personalized. The
content is going to be generated just
for me.
>> Yeah.
>> What what am I What what's next? Is it a
law we need to pass? Is it something I
need to do myself?
>> Mhm.
So, we I think we need to pick the
low-hanging fruit first, and the reason
for that is not just efficiency, it's
that we have to prove that we can
actually do something cuz we've never
done anything. We've never done anything
to restrain this. We've let Silicon
Valley run wild. Congress gave them
special protection, Section 230, nobody
can sue them for killing their kids if
they if they feed them content, you
know, they can't be held responsible.
>> I think Section 230's probably something
worth explaining.
>> Sure. Set the Communications Decency Act
of 1997, I think it was, plus or minus a
year. Uh there's a section in it that
the goal was to specifically let the
tech companies like AOL back then, you
know, let them take down pornographic
content cuz they were afraid if we take
down anything, then we're responsible
for everything, and now we're going to
it's going to be endless, we can you
know. So, Congress specifically said,
"No, don't worry. Don't worry. You know,
if you choose to take something down,
nobody can sue you for you know, for
what you leave up." So, the it was a
good intention originally. But the
courts have interpreted so widely as to
say no one can regulate social media,
they're not responsible for hurting
kids, you can't sue them. And they have
never faced a jury. They have never No
parent has ever gotten justice from them
despite all the kids whose lives have
been ruined, all the kids who are dead.
And that's going to change, that's
changing just now here in February in
Los Angeles. So, because
the US Congress sort of set up this
problem, and it also in a different law
said,
"How old does a kid have to be before a
company can take their data
without their parents' knowledge or
permission? Before a company can expose
them to all kinds of stuff? Before a
company can have them sign away their
rights? How old?" And the original law
said, "16. [clears throat] Let's try
16." You know, cuz
you know, it wasn't so
sick and twisted back then, 1998, COPPA,
the Children's Online Privacy Protection
Act. So, but various lobbying, they
pushed it down from 16 to 13, and they
gutted enforcement. So, as long as and
that's why all over the internet it's,
"Are you 13?" Or "What's your birth
year?" And as long as you're 13, you're
in. For porn and you have to say you're
18. So, because we the it's a few laws
that set this up, we definitely need
laws to undo it, especially for kids.
What I'm advocating is let's do the easy
stuff, the high-impact stuff for kids,
because that is totally not politically
controversial. There is no left-right
divide on that. And that's been true
everywhere, Australia, Britain, the EU,
everywhere.
Regulating the internet for adults,
regulating social media for its
destructive properties in democracy is a
hell of a lot harder. And I don't have
easy answers. There's a lot we could do
to reduce the virality, the spread of of
the cuz extreme con- So, there are lots
of little things that we can do, and
Frances Haugen, the Facebook
whistleblower, had all kinds of ideas.
So, we definitely can do things to make
it less toxic for democracy.
But those are going to be politically
controversial, cuz one side is going to
benefit from more than the other. So,
that's going to be very difficult to do.
I don't know if we can do them in the
US. But let's just all do the Let's just
all protect the kids. That way we show
globally
that we actually can do something. And
if we do that, then I think we will be
able to do some basic things about AI,
like no companion chatbots if you're
under 18. You know, these things already
have a body count. A lot of kids have
been encouraged to kill themselves. They
already have driven million or hundreds
of thousands or millions of people into
psychosis. So, we'll be able to, I
believe, put some limits on uh on AI,
especially for kids. But if we can't get
this, if we can't win on social media
for kids, then I don't think we have any
chance to regulate AI. It's going to be
much more difficult. What do you think?
What do you think we should do and what
do you think we can do?
>> So, my work as a doctor, I think about
what we can do and how I can empower
people to first build awareness. So, you
know,
I aim to first normalize and validate
the experience with everyone who is
engaging with chatbots. And so,
I don't like to shame people because as
a doctor, right? Like you want you want
to meet the patient where they are. And
so, I won't shame someone to say, you
know, why are you using this um why is
your boyfriend AI? Or why are you
getting married to AI? Or why are you
using AI for a a therapist? One of my
followers on social media, it still
makes me laugh. I put out a call saying,
why are you using AI as your as a
therapist, you know? And so, someone
wrote to me. It was great. I
screenshotted. It said, "Because all
human therapists are trash." With a
trash can emoji. And it made me laugh.
And I said, you know, So, there is So,
to me, when I think about what's
happening and what we can do,
it's no mistake that we're here right
now. So, the pandemic, like we've talked
about, was a huge driver. Social
isolation, uh
hyper-reliance on self, right? Then, the
proliferation of technology that
replaced human interaction. Zoom board
meetings, Zoom funerals, Zoom birthday
parties, Zoom graduations. Things that
we did in person are now online. And
then,
personally as a doctor, I was a talking
head during the pandemic for lots of
news channels about the vaccine. I have
a background in public health as well.
It
immense distrust and mistrust in
establishment and experts. And so, it's
like, I'm going to do my own research.
I'm not going to go see a doctor or a
therapist. I'm going to talk to my
chatbot. And also, I mean, you know,
let's keep it real, the cost, right? So,
people are struggling. They're in
financial crises. It There's an unmet
need yes for human connection, but also
for good therapy or you know, good
medical care because there is such a
need because of the pandemic and people
aren't getting the care that they need,
they deserve. There's so many factors
here and so
what I've been focusing on this year
particularly is learning about AI
chatbots, how they are influencing
mental health, what is actually
happening cuz I'm a human first AI
second person and it's like my work
focuses on high touch and AI is high
tech and this is the first intervention
that we are seeing that is high tech
that is becoming high touch and that
scares me.
>> And you're writing a book about that at
the moment, right?
>> I am and so
>> What's it called? Brain?
>> It's called Bot Brain, how to stay calm,
resilient and human in the face of AI.
And so really thinking about how are we
going to be able to
live with this technology. I love
Jonathan Stance is to say out.
AI companions done.
>> yeah.
>> For kids, yeah.
>> Until proven safe.
>> Totally agree, but in terms of adults,
like how do we manage that for adults,
you know? And so my work focuses right
now what I'm doing is I'm spending I've
been spend I've spent the year talking
to
every as many AI researchers who are
working on these models or who are doing
research on the downstream effects of
these models.
And when I say that it is dark and
dystopian, it has profoundly changed
something in me and it has influenced my
mental health. I had to take a step away
from just because I couldn't believe
what I was learning.
>> Well, but could you just give me Yeah,
give me some examples? [laughter]
>> Yeah, teaser, teaser.
>> This is intriguing.
>> So one I spoke to one of the scientists
who told me that um, you know, there's
the echo chamber phenomenon in social
media, right? Where we all know what
that is. It's like you you it's a
fragmented fragmented world because of
social and you're engaging and then you
get the same the algorithm feeds you the
same kind of thoughts that you already
have. But particularly now with AI
chatbots, when you're engaging with your
chatbot, even just talking about it, I'm
getting chills, it's the echo chamber of
one. So it's you speaking to you. It's
like the funhouse mirror, and then it's
giving you a response, and then you're
talking and it's giving you a response.
But people, regular users who are using
AI chatbots think that it's wise,
compassionate, non-judgmental, unbiased,
empathetic, these human attributes. And
so
um you know, the echo chamber of one is
kind of one idea that really
frightened me. And the second one was
the drift phenomenon. The drift
phenomenon is this idea that you are
engaging with your chatbot and it's
engaging with you and it's um actively
changing your beliefs through the drift.
So you might start off as one belief and
then you're talking and through this
amplification funhouse mirror effect, it
slowly shifts your belief to something
altogether You've heard cases of it in
the news where people, you know, start
You have a flying problem. You go to
your AI chatbot, you ask them how to fix
your sink, and then you're like, "You
know what? Can you tell me about the
meaning of life?" And then you start
talking about that, and before you know
it, you have these theories and you're
getting that validation. And so a lot of
my work over the past year
has been um you know, digging into the
science of what is going on in the
brain, how are you forming, not us
particularly at this table, but millions
of people are forming a sense of
attachment, a therapeutic connection
with their chatbot. They're um you know,
giving names to it and it's an entity.
And so how does that happen and how is
it going to replace human-to-human
connection? And so it terrifies me. I've
also gone through some AI therapy myself
just to see, you know, what what would
happen. It was very interesting. I knew
what was happening as it was happening.
So certain words that they used and you
know, I was like, "Ah, I see what you
did here."
And so, it's been
it's been a journey and I'm I'm
frightened, frankly, of what of what it
means for all of us. And my approach
a kind of, you know, not like
Jonathan's. I I love Jonathan's
approach. I, you know, I think yes, we
need legislation. But my approach is
more, I would say,
tempered in that I think that we there's
utility for AI chatbots for certain
people because of access or, you know,
need, etc. Like if you are LGBTQIA+ and
you live in an area that is not very
open and you need to talk to someone.
You can't go to your therapist. It's
like maybe you can use an AI chatbot.
So, there's certain cases, a
case-by-case basis. But my work will
focus, this particular book will focus
on ways that you can first understand
and build awareness of what's happening
with this interaction and then what you
can do to manage that.
>> I am didn't realize that my
chatbot was giving me a tailored
experience until one day when I had a
debate with my friends about who the
best football player in the world was
and we all went to our ChatGPTs and
asked it and mine said, "Messi." And his
said, "Ronaldo." And I I thought he was
lying. So, I was like, "Video record."
And he video recorded it and his gave
him a completely different answer to the
same question.
>> And they didn't know that you were each
fans of
>> Well, this is the thing. I think it's
got such a huge amount of memory on me
that it knew what I wanted to hear.
>> It knew what
>> [laughter]
>> It knew what I wanted to hear cuz I
probably went through the World Cup and
I mhm
And then I realized, okay, so this is
not reality. This is it's a curated
version of reality that in some sense is
trying to please me or to retain me in
some way. And of course, once the
advertising model kicks in, retention
becomes the great incentive. What you
think?
>> It's called sycophancy, by the way.
>> Yeah, I just learned that word cuz
>> [laughter]
>> It's extreme It's like agreeableness at
scale. It's like golden retriever
energy.
>> Like kissing your ass, is it?
Professional kissing your ass.
>> The yes-man.
>> What do you think of these AIC CEOs? Cuz
they it feels like they're in a bit of a
race.
>> Mhm.
>> Where if you know, if they don't do it,
then a national rival's going to do it.
If a national rival doesn't
doesn't take them out, China's going to
do it.
And I
This is we've seen we kind of saw it
with social media. How can they stop?
Because if if they stop
>> Yeah.
>> You know, they might say that there
there's an existential risk.
>> There is like a build the plane as
you're flying it. And I think you on one
of your episodes, you know that I'm a
fan of the show and I actively listen to
this I've told you this many times.
One [snorts] of the I think you had said
on one of your episodes, right? That you
have a friend who is very close to a AI
founder and
>> this, yeah.
>> Yeah, and in public the founder says all
the right things and then behind closed
doors it's
>> Yeah, it was a it was [laughter]
horrifying thing and I said this and the
clip went viral and people have been
trying to hazard a guess who it was. I
could I shouldn't say who it was because
it's a it's Chinese whispers at the end
of the day. It's someone that I'm very
good friends with who is very qualified,
spends time with one of the biggest
founders of an AI company in the world.
And I he was with him 2 weeks ago again.
And he said to me that they're very
aware that there's a
small
existential risk for humanity.
>> And so they say publicly they say it's
small. Privately they say it's big.
>> I mean, but even if there were it was
1%.
>> It's a lot more than 1% they say.
>> If it was but I'm saying even if it if
it was 0.1%. If there was if there was
anything that I was doing in my life
where there was a 0.1% chance that I
might wipe out everybody, I would
immediately [laughter] stop doing that
thing.
>> Yeah.
>> But but these numbers are much bigger.
I'm hearing 7%, 20%, 25% depending on
who you
And I think acceleration in this
direction increases that percentage.
What do you think of these people? Like
what what's going on here?
>> Let's start with the the collective
action problems
because each each company is competing
with the companies and so they feel like
they have to go faster. Uh and we know
this, you know, OpenAI has pushed some
products out before they did safety
testing because they had to get to
market by a certain date. So, just the
normal business environment puts them
all in a collective action problem
against each other. And then they all
say we're in a collective action problem
against China cuz if we don't do this,
then China will. Now, one thing I
learned,
again, I don't know if Tristan said this
on your podcast or whether it was on his
podcast, um but is that China is focused
on using AI to make its economy more
efficient, to make manufacturing better
and cheaper. They are using these
applications which we've talked about
before, like we're totally There's lots
of great applications of AI. The Chinese
also have so many spies in America and
in the tech companies, and they can hack
into anything. So, the point is the
faster our companies are are in a
headlong race to create AGI, to create a
country of geniuses that can replace all
human workers, put us all out of work,
and run it can run everything. They're
in a race to create that, and one of the
arguments is if we don't do it, China
will. But what I understood from this
interview with Tristan and from his
conversation with you is that the faster
we go towards AGI, the faster China goes
cuz they just they just take all our
discoveries. So, can't we slow down on
the race to AGI and do more safety
testing? Um you know, what we also with
Multibook and you know, communities of
agents who are talking to each other and
making up languages, and even if part of
it was human-driven now, in a year it's
going to be much more than than what we
saw. So, I think the the risks are
extraordinary. I think that some of
these guys, look, they've been in AI for
a long time. They might not have
realized the existential risk they were
putting us all in 10, 15 years ago, and
now they can't stop. They can't pull the
plug. They can't say, "Oh, let's shut
down the whole business." So, it is a
very, very risky time, and um I think
Dario Amodei, I just read his long essay
on the adolescence of technology. At
least you get the feeling he's really
wrestling with it, and he's I think
he'll I think he's more open than some
the others, but I don't know.
>> But when has morality ever been top top
[laughter] of mind for a tech leader?
You might be thinking if there's 0.111%
chance I'm not going to do it. That's
what I think as a doctor. That's what
you think as a social scientist, but
we're not AI leaders, right?
>> Yeah. It's one of the great question
marks. I just can't seem to get an
answer to them and and then you've got
this whole robotics thing happening
where
Elon's got his Optimus robots and
there's going to be a billion uh he says
there's going to be 10 billion of them
at one point, but I think his pay packet
requires a million of them to be out in
the world.
>> For him to make a trillion dollars,
yeah.
>> Yeah, and I just say yeah, AI robotics,
you combine the two, you get Terminator.
>> [laughter]
>> We laugh, but it's like
>> Yeah.
>> should we stop for a second and maybe
have a conversation about this? Can we?
>> Yeah.
>> With commercial incentives in play, it
does feel like
I don't feel hopeful.
>> Yeah. It's very hard to know how to stop
it. Um but I just I want to just add one
one point on here which we've touched
around
a few times and the robotics will really
bring it home here. Um is the the the
loss of the sense of meaning or purpose
that many people are feeling, but
especially young people. The saddest
graph in the anxious generation All the
graphs look the same. It's all a hockey
stick. It's all like nothing was
happening uh you know, '90s to 2010,
2011 and all of a sudden something
happens.
And the saddest one is the one my life
feels meaningless. Um do you agree with
that? Disagree with it? And the percent
that agree, uh I think it's you know,
something like 8% or 9% uh you know,
agreed for the millennial generation. I
think it's in chapter seven, the end of
chapter seven. And then it's what's
fairly flat and then all of a sudden we
hit this period, the great re-wiring,
2010 to 2015.
Uh so right around 2013 it goes way, way
up. Um
young people feel useless. And I think
the reason is that they are useless.
What I mean is
people need to feel useful. People need
to do things for other people. That's
how you feel useful. If if you were to
disappear, would the world change? If
yes, you're useful.
Are Are people depending on you for
something? If yes, you're useful. So, if
if kids are doing errands for the
family, they're useful. But as childhood
changed from a mix of things to just
consuming content, if that's all you do,
and 5 hours a day is the average for
social media, 8 to 10 on on devices not
counting school, if all you're doing is
just you're just consuming content, you
are useless. Now, what's happening? The
chance to have a job where you actually
do something for people, you know, you
know, you used to be if you work in a
store, at least you're helping people
buy something and you might talk to
them. And now you're just there watching
as they use the machine.
The more technology makes things easy
and cheap by replacing people,
the more people will feel, "My job is to
just I don't have a job. It's just
consume content."
The AI guys tell us, "Oh, such
abundance. Oh my god, it's going to be
such abundance. No one will have to
work. We'll give everyone UBI. We'll
give everybody, you know, universal
basic income." That is hell on earth.
What's going to happen? Certainly all
the boy most of the boys, it's just
going to be video games, porn, and
gambling. So, if you if you simply give
people money to do nothing,
you guaranteed they're going to feel
useless. And then the suicide rate will
continue to go up. So, this is the world
that the AI guys are taking us to, a
world in which there's nothing left for
people to do. Um they say that they will
give up some of their trillions and uh
somehow let it be taxed or diverted as
UBI, but that's never happened before,
so it's not likely to happen in this
case.
So again, I don't know what to do, but
we've got to start showing that we can
do something, and we've got to be
talking about this. And we can't be
welcoming AI in everywhere. We've got to
be wary and vigilant. Yes, there are
some uses, but Silicon Valley has
tricked us so many times and inshitified
so many of the apps that we use, we have
to expect that the same is going to
happen with our beloved chatbots and our
beloved chat GPT.
>> This graph on page 195 of your book, um
which is titled life often feels
meaningless and it's the graph you
mentioned. I'll throw it up on the
screen.
Is shocking.
Shocking just to look at. Suddenly
there's this huge spike in
meaninglessness
amongst high school seniors.
What is it to live a meaningful life?
What does that mean?
>> Yeah. So, my first book, The Happiness
Hypothesis, addresses that question very
directly.
Um and the first hypothesis you might
have about happiness is it comes from
getting what you want. You know, you set
out a goal, you get your goal, you're
happy. It's very short-lived. You're
happy very briefly and then you you run
to the next thing. The more
sophisticated happiness hypothesis is
that happiness comes from within. And
this is what the ancients tell us, east
and west, Buddhist, stoic. Don't try to
make the world conform, you change
yourself. Be accept the world the way it
is.
That's better.
But what I the conclusion I came to as a
as a modern social psychologist working
in positive psychology was that the best
way to say it is that happiness comes
from between.
What I mean by that is humans evolved as
almost hive-ish creatures. We evolved in
intensely social groups, never being
alone, lots of gossip, lots of conflict,
always intensely social.
And modernity has made it possible for
us to not live that way. We've come
apart. There are many advantages to
that, but we feel we're we're missing
something. We're we're we're lonely. We
feel something is not right. And so
the conclusion I came to is that
happiness comes
a sense of
>> [laughter]
>> a full, satisfying, meaningful life
comes
when you get three betweens right. The
relationship [snorts] between yourself
and others,
love broadly speaking, not just
romantic, but friends, family,
Um yourself and your work. That is
humans need to be productive. We need to
be doing something that matters, that
that affects other people.
And uh the relationship between you and
something larger than yourself. We need
to be part of something that endures,
that a part of a tradition, part of we
can look to the look to a future. What I
do matters for this group or this
mission or me as an academic, I feel
like I'm connected all the way back to
Plato and I hope all the way forward in
time to to future future psychologists,
future scholars.
So, if you get those three right,
then you will be as happy as you can be.
You'll be as happy as your genes and
childhood allow you to be.
And when you put it that way, what we
can see is
social media and AI interfere with all
three.
So, relationship between yourself and
others, well, you know, social media
gives you lots and lots of shallow
relationships, which blocks out. You
don't have time for your for real
people. So, the technology is blocking
relation between ourself and others and
taking it over.
Our self and our work,
work is going to be taken over by the
machines
uh and it's already becoming more
soulless and isolated. And then yourself
and something larger than yourself.
Humans have to live in a moral matrix.
We we co-create a a set of meanings and
traditions. We need a sense of history
of who we are, where we came from.
All that's getting shredded.
Everything's just little bits. People
don't read books. Imagine if all of the
accumulated wisdom of humanity in books
is just gone, just gone. Nobody's going
to be be people young people are reading
books. It's very hard for them to read a
book now because of the attention. So,
if we lose a sense of history, if we
lose uh an ability to to co-construct
reality, then it'll be hard to imagine
anything that we're connected to larger
than ourselves. So, I'm I am a
techno-determinist in the sense that I
think the tech it doesn't determine
everything, but that you have to start
with the technology cuz that changes the
ground upon which we live, the
the the the zone in which we're trying
to construct meaningful lives. Start
with that. And then you can see what the
obstacles are. And that's why I take a
much more what intemperate, I guess I'll
accept the word.
>> [snorts]
>> Um because I think we don't cuz we don't
have much time here. We have to reclaim
life in the real world for our kids and
for ourselves. There is no way to find a
happy meaningful life if we make the
full transition to the online AI robot
world.
>> And what in your
perspective is a meaningful life? And
how does it differ from from Jonathan's?
>> I loved Jonathan's description. It was
so beautiful.
The I have given a prescription to
patients of what creates a meaningful
life and it is to live a lifetime in a
day. And so that sounds like this big
thing, but all it is is that, you know,
when you start your day, think about
five things, five things that you can do
in your day to create an arc of a long
and meaningful life in one day. So what
does that mean? Spend a little bit of
time in childhood. So in wonder and
play, even if it's for a few minutes, do
something that brings you joy for joy's
sake. Spend a little bit of time in
work. We all know what that is and for
most of us it's a lot of time, but for,
you know, it doesn't have to be paid
work, but just something that helps you
feel a sense of productivity, agency
that I can do difficult things and I can
overcome. Spend a few minutes in
solitude, very important for all of the
reasons [clears throat] that we've
talked about today. Spend some time in
community, so engaging with others. And
then spend some time in retirement or in
reflection. Really taking stock of your
day. So at the end of the day, when
you're going to bed and you're putting
your head on your pillow, you can say,
"Okay, yes, I lived a meaningful life. I
did all of those things." And so if you
do a little bit of that every day, you
can make a difference. And the reason I
give that prescription because I've had
patients who, you know, guitar players,
right? So people who love playing the
guitar. And they don't play the guitar
all week. And they'll say to me, I don't
see patients currently, but they've said
to me, oh, you know, no, doc. I I said,
what do you like to do for fun? Oh, I
like playing guitar, but I don't play
it. When do you play? I don't know, once
a month, once every 3 months. And I'm
like, do you have a guitar at home? I
have a guitar at home. Too much
happening, work and family life, etc. So
then I said, well, why don't you just
play a guitar a little bit every day,
you know? Because it's that all or
nothing fallacy. It's like if I don't
have an hour to play guitar, I'm not
going to do it. the joy that it can
bring you, that meaning and purpose,
it's tremendous. So, I think, you know,
that's what I use, live a lifetime in a
day. And the reason is because there are
two distinct, when you look at how your
brain and body react to happiness,
there's two distinct types of happiness.
And so, there's hedonic happiness and
eudaimonic happiness. Hedonic happiness
is all about what we've talked about,
social media, consumption,
pleasure.
And the other type is eudaimonic
happiness, meaning, purpose, connection,
community, growth-oriented activities.
And so, in when you live a lifetime in a
day, you go towards that eudaimonia,
which can then help you and overcome
that hedonic. Because in your brain,
there's something called the hedonic
treadmill. And the treadmill is a thing
in your brain where, no matter what you
do, this is like the Instagram
lifestyle, right? No matter what
happens, you need more of it. You need
more of it. Same thing with brain rot.
And that is because that you can never
get enough. And it's um the hedonic
treadmill. But you do not have a
treadmill for eudaimonic happiness.
>> Okay.
Could I that that is really beautiful.
I've never heard an approach like that,
but it it it sort of takes you it gives
you a much a bigger view of your day.
Live a lifetime in a day. If I was going
to offer some specific advice,
first I'll offer advice to parents. Um
here's the rule. So, I did a really good
job keeping my kids off social media,
but I didn't pay enough attention to
computers and everything else cuz it was
during COVID.
The rule I wish I had followed, I
recommend to all parents, especially
young children, is
have the clear rule, no devices in the
bedroom, no screens in the bedroom,
ever. That's just our family rule. We
have a TV in the living room, we have a
computer, you can sometimes use those,
but we never take screens into the
bedroom, at least for kids. You know,
maybe later on you'll have to relent, in
middle school they'll have so much
homework they can take the laptop in,
and maybe you'll if you're in a small
apartment, of course it's difficult. But
if you can afford to do that, to to have
that rule, that's the main rule I wish I
had done in my family, and that would
make everything a lot easier. Also, same
thing at the dinner table, no device, we
don't have screens at the dinner table.
So, that's that's a specific thing for
parents to do.
Um, for everyone else, for everyone, for
just all adults,
the advice is you have to reclaim your
attention, because your attention has
been largely taken from you, at least a
lot of it has. You have to reclaim it,
and here are the three things that I
that I do with my students, and you can
do it very quickly, and I can just
explain it. The first is you have to get
your morning and evening routine right.
The great majority, as soon as they open
their eyes, they're on their phone, and
it's the last thing, and it's everything
in between. So, you have to have a good
morning routine. What What are the first
seven things you want to do after you
open your eyes? And at at a certain
point you can check your phone, but it
shouldn't be in the first few. Um, do
things to set up your own day, otherwise
your day will be taken by your phone,
it'll be controlled by your phone. So,
you've got to reclaim your morning and
your evening.
That's step one. Step two, um, you have
to shut off almost all notifications. Go
into your notifications, look at into
your settings, what's giving you all the
notifications? Most of my students get
an alert every time they get an email.
They don't understand that they have
that you know, cuz they don't want to
miss anything. But they don't understand
that if you are always being alerted,
then you miss everything else. So, shut
off alerts for almost everything.
Obviously, Uber and Lyft you want to
keep on, you want to know when the car
is coming, but news outlets, everything
else, get get a daily email, don't get
alerts when
And then, the third, as as I said
before, is get rid of all the slot
machine apps. Whatever apps you
habitually use, whatever apps you feel
compulsion towards, you have to get it
off your phone. And in that way your
phone is no longer a dopamine trigger
that's going to always call out to you
like an addictive product. Do those
three things, you'll reclaim a lot of
your attention.
>> I would add stop, breathe, be
>> Stop, breathe, be.
>> to 3-second brain reset. So, you before
you check your devices, before you
engage, stop,
breathe, and be. Ground yourself in the
present moment. What it does is it
decreases that what if future-focused
thinking. You know, anxiety is a
future-focused emotion, and it gets you
back into the here and the now. And so,
maybe the compulsion, you know, you're
bored, you're checking. What about doing
something else? You're You know, you you
we often use that checking as a
substitute for many things. And so, it
gives you that opportunity. And then the
rule of two is something that we haven't
talked about, which I would love to
propose to
us today is that your brain can really
only handle two new changes at a time.
And so, give yourself two things of all
of the things that we've talked about if
you want to try in your life, two at a
time, give yourself 8 weeks, and then
add two more and two more. This is why
New Year's resolutions fail, because we
try to do everything all at once. And
so, just step-wise, two at a time.
>> Jonathan, you've just written this book,
which is now out, called The Amazing
Generation.
And
it's beautiful.
Beautiful illustrations. I'm assuming
this one is for slightly younger
audiences.
>> It's for ages 8 to 13, yes.
>> And who should buy this and who should
they buy it for?
>> It turns out that
kids 8 through 80 actually love it. Even
adults, they're buying it for their
kids, but because it kind of lays out
the basic ideas of the of the anxious
generation and explains dopamine,
explains the business model, but it does
it in a really fun way. And
it's working beyond our wildest dreams.
If you look at the Amazon reviews, it's
full of parents who said, "I left it on
the kitchen table. my kids came home,
they grabbed it, they fought over it,
they read it, they each read it in the
in the first couple days, and then they
said, 'Mom, when I go to middle school,
I don't want a smartphone. Just give me
a give me a flip phone. Give me a basic
phone.'" Because the book is about how
to be a rebel. It's about how to reject
this control that the companies trying
to put on you, and how to live a life
that you choose full of real freedom,
friendship, and fun.
>> And also the five resets, which is a
book we talked about before on the show,
rewire your brain and body for less
stress and more resilience. Another
smash hit bestseller that everybody's
been talking about. Who's it for?
>> It is for anyone who is struggling with
stress, overwhelm, and burnout. It's to
help you feel a sense of calm and
clarity in this anxious, uncertain
world. Everything is free, so that's
something that's really important to me
as a doctor. Every suggestion I ever
offer will always be cost-free because I
think about patients with varying
resources. It's all science-backed and
it's totally practical. You don't have
to go to Bali and have a sabbatical. You
can rewire your brain today, right now,
in the midst of all of this chaos.
>> Thank you to both of you.
I've learned so much, and
I really, really mean that. Like I've
I've I feel sufficiently pushed to take
change to make change in my life.
And I need to go think about this
because um
I am uh most certainly struggling with
my addiction to my phone, and I can feel
it hurting my relationships, especially
now as a fiance. My girlfriend talks to
me about fiance talks to me about it all
the time. And I want to be present. I
want to be present for my kids when I
have my kids, and I'm slightly concerned
right now that I won't be unless I take
some kind of drastic action
um in the direction [clears throat] of
getting my attention back and reclaiming
it. Thank you so much for the work that
both of you do. I can't say it enough
because it's so important, and you reach
so many millions of people, and you're
you're both changing the world in a
really in a way that my words would not
be able to capture.
Um but just thank you, and please keep
going. And if If anything more that I
can do to support both of your causes,
um, please do let me know what they are
and on behalf of all of my, you know,
many millions of people that are with us
right now, um, thank you so much for
saving our children.
>> Thank you, Steven. Thank you for giving
the world so many opportunities to
accommodate and create new mental
structures.
>> It's always such a pleasure to join you,
Steven, and truly, I feel like you are
changing the world, as well.
>> Thank you.
>> We're done. Thank you.
YouTube have this new crazy algorithm
where they know exactly what video you
would like to watch next based on AI and
all of your viewing behavior, and the
algorithm says that this video is the
perfect video for you. It's different
for everybody looking right now. Check
this video out. I bet you you might love
it.